<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The guard of the tree of life, or, A sacramental discourse shewing a Christians priviledge in approaching to God in ordinances, duty in his sacramentall approaches, danger if hee do not sanctifie God in them / by Samuel Bolton ...</title>
            <author>Bolton, Samuel, 1606-1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 92 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28622</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3520</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33239</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13110184</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13110184</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97618</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28622)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97618)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1544:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The guard of the tree of life, or, A sacramental discourse shewing a Christians priviledge in approaching to God in ordinances, duty in his sacramentall approaches, danger if hee do not sanctifie God in them / by Samuel Bolton ...</title>
                  <author>Bolton, Samuel, 1606-1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 166 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. Simmons for A. Kembe, and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sacraments.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97618:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97618:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GUARD OF THE Tree of Life: OR, A Sacramentall Diſcourſe; SHEWING A Chriſtians
<list>
                  <item>Priviledge, in approaching to God in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</item>
                  <item>Duty, in his Sacramentall approaches.</item>
                  <item>Danger, if hee do not ſanctifie God in them.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By SAMUEL BOLTON, Preacher to the Congregation of <hi>Saviours South-warke.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 11.27.</hi>
               </bibl> Whoſoever ſhall eat this Bread, and drink this Cup of the Lord unworthily, ſhall be guilty of the body and blood of the Lord.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Verſe 29.</hi>
               </bibl> Hee eateth and drinketh damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to himſelf, not diſcerning the Lords body.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. Simmons</hi> for <hi>A. Kembe,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the <hi>Talbot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi> in <hi>Southwark,</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:97618:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97618:2"/>
            <head>TO MY BELOVED FRIENDS, The Godly and Well-affected of <hi>Saviours-Southwark;</hi> Grace and Peace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now well-nigh four yeeres ſince I was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from a loving, a very loving people in the City, and fixed among you; the expreſſes of love which in this time I have received from you, have put me on to think, what way I might again manifeſt my ingagements to you: And conſidering with my ſelf the relation wherein I ſtand, I could
<pb facs="tcp:97618:3"/>think of no better way of acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement then to impart ſomething ſpirituall to you; and no better ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject then this which is now preſented to your view, nor could I think of a better time then this for the doing of it, when God in our blood ſhewes us what a fearfull thing it is to be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the blood of his Sonne; It is not unknown unto you, how greatly this place above many others, hath been guilty of the prophanation of this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the Lords Supper; God hath diſcovered it to us, humbled us for it, ſhewed us the neceſsity, and graciouſly inclined your ſpirits to the deſire of the reformation of it. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to which (through the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and aſsiſtance of you) my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Miniſter and my ſelf, have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured to ſet upon the work, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing to put our ſelves to no little trouble, if by that wee might prevent a great deal of ſin. In this work (the ſearcher of hearts knowes) we have had no other deſign, then to
<pb facs="tcp:97618:3"/>expreſs our Paſtorall duties, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare our Paſtorall affections towards your ſouls: In ſhort, to ſerve you in love: Probably we may meet with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny obſtacles in the carrying on this work; Indeed, it is that which is expected; nay, and that which wee reckoned on before we entred on it. But if the work be Gods, hee will either facilitate and make it eaſie for us, or give us ſpirits proportionable to the greatneſs of it, I ſay hee will either leſſen the difficulties, or heigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten our ſpirits to conflict and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with them.</p>
            <p>There are two ſort of adverſaries which we expect to meet withall: ſome that will ſay, we go too far, and others who will blame us that we go no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>To them that think we have gone too far, I ſhall only ſay, that we hope we have not gone beyond Gods bounds; ſure as God hath a purpoſe this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance ſhould be continued, ſo hee
<pb facs="tcp:97618:4"/>hath a care alſo, that it ſhould be fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from prophanation in the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of it; and when a better way ſhall be diſcovered to us, wherein we may hold up the uſe of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and yet fence it (in the uſe of it) from evident prophanation, wee are ready to liſten to it, and be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for it; in the mean, wee do not ſee it our duty to hold up the uſe of this Ordinance, except there be ſome fence ſet up (all former fences being inſufficient, and now broken down) to keep this Ordinance from mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt prophanation, unleſs you will ſay our Paſtorall office doth, in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of it, neceſsitate us to ſin. Much more might be ſaid, if wee ſaw it ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther requiſite or convenient for an Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>To thoſe who blame us we go no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I muſt ſay our deſign hath bin ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to tempt on, by going their pace, then to diſcourage by over-driving our little ones; I ſay it hath been our
<pb facs="tcp:97618:4"/>aim to cheriſh not to quench, to draw out, not to ſuppreſs the graces of our people; and therefore have we deſired to improve thoſe graces which wee found, though weak, rather then to expect that which was not to be found. Our preſent reformation, it is not the meaſure of our will, but of our power; it is not the utmoſt wee deſire, but the utmoſt wee are able: And though it may ſeem ſmall to you, yet deſpiſe not the day of ſmall things; though the houſe is not built, yet wee rejoyce the firſt ſtone is laid, and wee could not chooſe but bring it forth with ſhouting, Grace, Grace, unto it, and Glory, Glory to the Lord. <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> was not built in a day, neither is <hi>Sion;</hi> God carries on his works without us, as he doth his works with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us, by degrees; the greateſt fire was at firſt a ſpark, the talleſt Oak at the firſt an Achorne, the ſtrongeſt Chriſtian had his infancie, and the greateſt work of God its mean begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings;
<pb facs="tcp:97618:5"/>Would the corruption of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times have ſuffered our godly predeceſſours, to have left the work in that forwardneſs to us, in which through Gods bleſsing, it may be left to them who ſhall ſucceed, poſsibly, nay probably, the work might have been carryed on to a greater height then now it can; That which is done wee deſire to bleſs God for it, and think it our duty to cheriſh with our utmoſt prayers and indeavours; In relation to which, theſe enſuing Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons formerly preached, are now printed, to which work, if they ſhall be any thing ſerviceable, they have obtained the end of him,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Who is not unwilling to ſpend, and be ſpent for you: S. BOLTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:97618:5"/>
            <head>A briefe Table of the maine things contained in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſcourſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Introduction into the Diſcourſe and parts of the Text, and expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the term.</hi> pag 1, 2, 3, 4.</item>
               <item>Doctr. 1. <hi>To have to do with an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, is to draw neer to God.</hi> p. 7.</item>
               <item>Uſe 1. <hi>Judge how much you are bound to God for Ordinances.</hi> p. 10.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>What cauſe to lament the ſad conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe that want them.</hi> p. 11, 12.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>What a ſin to diſturb the Saints in the uſe of Ordinances.</hi> p. 13.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>See the ground the Saints ſo much ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with Ordinances.</hi> p. ibid.</item>
               <item>5. <hi>See what cauſe there is to keep our hearts in a holy frame.</hi> p. 14.</item>
               <item>Uſe. Exhort. 1. <hi>To a conſcionable uſe of Ordinances, upon four grounds.</hi> p. 20. to 25.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>To conſcionablneſs in the uſe of them upon three grounds.</hi> p. 26, <hi>to</hi> 28.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>To</hi> Exhort, <hi>When ever you have to do with Ordiuances, take Chriſt with you,</hi> p. 30</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The neceſſity of it:</hi> 1. <hi>In regard of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion:</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97618:6"/>2. <hi>Aſſiſtance:</hi> 3. <hi>Acceptance.</hi> pag. 31, 32, 33.</item>
               <item>Doct. 2. <hi>Thoſe who have to do with God in an Ordinance, muſt ſanctifie God in it.</hi> 34.</item>
               <item>1. <hi>What it is to ſanctifie God in an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance.</hi> 35.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>To which ſomething is required:</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 <hi>In the work.</hi> 35.</item>
                           <item>2 <hi>The work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>In his head, knowledge,</hi> &amp;c. 36.</item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>In his heart.</hi> 36.
<list>
                                       <item>1. <hi>Holy affections</hi>
                                       </item>
                                       <item>2. <hi>Sutable.</hi> 37.</item>
                                       <item>3. <hi>Excited.</hi> 38.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>How we muſt ſanctifie God in this ordinance.</hi> p. 40
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Something is required before.</hi> 41.
<list>
                           <item>1 <hi>Habituall</hi> 43.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>preparation.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <hi>Actuall</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Something in the time.</hi> 44.
<list>
                           <item>1 <hi>Exerciſe of Grace.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <hi>Sutable demeanors.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Faith</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Repentance.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>1 <hi>Faith, where is diſcovered:</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>What act of faith.</hi> 45.</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon what object.</hi> 50.</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>For what benefits.</hi> 54.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Faith is to be exerciſed for four benefits in the Sacrament:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>1. <hi>For the further aſſurance of our ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification.</hi> 56.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>For the increaſe of ſanctification.</hi> 59.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>For the ſubduing of corruptions.</hi> 70.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>For deliverance out of temptation.</hi> 74.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>And how faith is to be acted upon Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:97618:6"/>for theſe benefits, is diſcovered.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The ſecond Grace to be exerciſed in the time, is Repentance.</hi> pag. 78.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Where is ſet down:</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1 <hi>The kindes of mourning.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>Hiſtoricall.</hi> 79.</item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>Spirituall. 79.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2 <hi>The advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages to it.</hi> 82.
<list>
                                 <item>1 <hi>The diſcovery of love.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 <hi>Sufferings of Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Theſe are the Graces required in the time; now the demanours,</hi> p. 89.</item>
               <item>1. <hi>An humble reverence:</hi> 2. <hi>Diſcharge of worldly thoughts.</hi> p. 90.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Something is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired afterward to ſanctifie God in this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance.</hi> p. 93.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thankfulnes.</hi> 94</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Obedience.</hi> 98.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Why we muſt ſanctifie God.</hi> 3. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. p. 103.
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Becauſe God commands.</hi> 103.</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Becauſe otherwiſe get no good.</hi> p. 105.</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Becauſe otherwiſe get hurt.</hi> p. 107.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Vſe <hi>Of complaint. How few do ſanctifie God in this ordinance.</hi> p. 100.</item>
               <item>2 Vſe <hi>Examination; Whether you have ſanctified God in it.</hi> p. 112.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Before</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>See if you have obſerved God's order.</hi> p. 113. 114.</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>See whether obſerved God's rules.</hi> p. 16.</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>See whether you have obſerved God's ends.</hi> p. 118.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:97618:7"/>
               <item>2 <hi>See if you have exerciſed Gods gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the time.</hi> p. 123.</item>
               <item>3 <hi>See whether wee have returned home with God's quicknings and refreſhments.</hi> p. ibid.</item>
               <item>3 Doctr. <hi>God will be ſanctified of every one that doth not ſanctifie him in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</hi> p. 130.</item>
               <item>1 <hi>What is meant by God's ſanctifying himſelf on men.</hi> p. 131.</item>
               <item>2 <hi>What are the reaſons why God doth ſanctifie himſelf on thoſe who do not ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him in ordinances.</hi> p. 132.</item>
               <item>6 Reaſons of it:
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>For terrour and dread of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſons.</hi> p. 133.</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>For caution to others.</hi> p. 134.</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>To declare his juſtice.</hi> p. 136</item>
                     <item>4 <hi>To remove ſcandall.</hi> p. 137.</item>
                     <item>5 <hi>To hold up his great name.</hi> p. 148.</item>
                     <item>6 <hi>To declare his hatred againſt ſin.</hi> p. 142.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Vſe, <hi>Caution to prophane perſons.</hi> 143.</item>
               <item>Vſe, <hi>To exhort us to turn our eyes back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and examine whether wee have not been guilty of the prophanation of this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance.</hi> p. 151.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:97618:7"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>The triall is put upon three further deſignes.</hi> pag. 151.</item>
               <item>1 Sign. <hi>If the Sacraments have wrought no further good upon thee.</hi> p. ibid.</item>
               <item>2 Sign. <hi>If thou art worſe after then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</hi> p. 153.</item>
               <item>3 Sign. <hi>If thou haſt fed upon nothing but outward elements, thou hast been a prophaner of this ordinance.</hi> p. 156.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A briefe rehearſall and application of the whole to wicked and unregenerate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Downam.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:97618:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97618:8"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LEVIT. 10.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Then Moſes ſaid unto Aaron, This is that the Lord ſpake, ſaying, I will bee ſanctified in them that come nigh me.—</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E are all here preſent <hi>met together</hi> at an <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> and many of us have <hi>intended</hi> to goe upon a further <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</hi> And there is no man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who hath to doe with any <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance</hi> of God, but hath <hi>to deale</hi> with <hi>God</hi> in it, he drawes neere to God. And God hath ſaid he will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>ſanctified</hi> in all them that <hi>draw <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eere</hi> to him; either he will be <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by you,</hi> in your <hi>active glorifying</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f him, or <hi>upon you,</hi> in your <hi>paſsive</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earing his diſpleaſure.
<note place="margin">A te, vel De te.</note> There is never <hi>a one</hi> of you here preſent, but God will be <hi>ſanctified</hi> and glorified
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97618:9"/>in you this day. And 'tis my <hi>ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire</hi> that you may all <hi>actively</hi> glorifie God, that he may not <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively</hi> glorifie himſelfe upon you, and raiſe his glory out of the ruines of any of you.</p>
            <p>I need not <hi>travell</hi> farre back to find you a <hi>coherence,</hi> the verſe before will afford it; And the firſt word of my <hi>Text</hi> bids me go no further.</p>
            <p>There is,
<list>
                  <item>1. The occaſion of theſe words.</item>
                  <item>2. The Preface to them.</item>
                  <item>3. The words themſelves.</item>
                  <item>4. The effect of them.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>occaſion</hi> of theſe words, and that was the untimely death of <hi>Aarons</hi> two ſonnes, their <hi>death</hi> gave <hi>birth</hi> to theſe words. And a ſentence it is not too deare, if bought with the lives of thouſands of men. 2. The <hi>Preface</hi> to them, This is that the Lord ſaid; why, where did the Lord <hi>ſpeak</hi> it? Did he ſpeak it to <hi>Moſes</hi> only? or did he ſpeak it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the Congregation alſo? we never reade it was <hi>booked</hi> before, <hi>totidem
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97618:9"/>verbis.</hi> Some think this <hi>puniſhment</hi> was all the command they had, but I cannot think, that God doth <hi>firſt puniſh,</hi> and thereupon raiſe a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, but he firſt <hi>gives</hi> his Law, then <hi>puniſhes</hi> the breach of it.</p>
            <p>And the words <hi>declare</hi> there had been ſome <hi>charge</hi> given, <hi>This is that the Lord ſaid,</hi> ſo that there was ſome charge. But where was it? Wee read not of it here. Some ſay it was <hi>ſpoken,</hi> but not <hi>written;</hi> and this they would have to countenance their <hi>unwritten traditions.</hi> Some will have it, in <hi>Exo.</hi> 19.22. <hi>Let the Prieſts ſanctifie themſelves, leſt the Lord break in upon them.</hi> Others will have it in <hi>Levit.</hi> 8.35, 36. <hi>Keep the Lord's charge that you die not. Calvin</hi> will not have it referred to any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar place, but a generall charge, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at divers times; and now the preſent occaſion brings it forth to particular application, to which I aſſent. 3. Wee have the words
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97618:10"/>themſelves, <hi>I will be ſanctified.</hi> Why, what is that? Can God be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of us? Indeed he ſanctifies us, but how can we ſanctifie him?</p>
            <p>God is ſanctified two wayes:
<list>
                  <item>1. Actively.</item>
                  <item>2. Paſſively.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Actively, as 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie the Lord in your hearts;</hi> and thus God is ſanctified, when wee <hi>cheriſh</hi> and maintain high <hi>eſteems of God</hi> in our hearts, when we do ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, eſteem, and advance God in our hearts, and in our lives.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Paſſively, by puniſhing of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28.22. <hi>When I have executed my judgement on her,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio Dei, eſt poena pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantium.</hi> Jerom.</note> 
               <hi>then ſhall I be ſanctified in her. Jerome</hi> on this place ſaith, <hi>The puniſhment of offenders, is the ſanctification of God;</hi> So you ſee it was in the Text, God was <hi>ſanctified</hi> on them, not by their <hi>doing good,</hi> but by their <hi>ſuffering evill;</hi> not Actively, but Paſſively: And in both theſe ſenſes the words are to be read, I ſay the words are to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97618:10"/>be read in this disjunctive ſenſe, <hi>I will be ſanctified of all them that draw neer to me,</hi> that is, either actively, in glorifying me in the work; or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively, in glorifying my ſelf upon the workman;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Si volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas Dei non fiat a te, fiet de te.</hi> Aug.</note> if you do not ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie God in an Ordinance, he will be ſanctified upon you. 4. We have the effect of theſe words upon <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>it ſtruck him dumb;</hi> a dutifull dumbneſs; he was ſilent to <hi>Jehovah,</hi> he held his peace; he was dumb, &amp; opened not his mouth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was God's doing.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Silet audita voluntate Dei.</hi> Calv.</note> God's will being manifeſt, it chained up his tongue, he held his peace; thereby confeſſing, ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iuſto Dei judicio ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinctos eſſe.</note> 
               <hi>that they were ſlain by the juſt judgement of God.</hi> His ſilence cleared God in his deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. And what a power is there then in faith, and grace; to ſilence the ſoul in ſuch a ſad condition as this? The <hi>loſs</hi> of his ſons, his <hi>el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt</hi> ſons, when <hi>young,</hi> and without poſterity, in the <hi>firſt</hi> day of their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97618:11"/>miniſtration, in the <hi>ſight</hi> of all the Congregation, and by ſo fearfull a judgement, <hi>fire</hi> from the Lord, and in the <hi>act</hi> of their <hi>ſin,</hi> which ſome think was joyned with drunkenneſs too, whereupon the prohibition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt wine follows, v. 9: ſo that the Congregation might ſuſpect they went but from fire to fire, from a <hi>deſtruction</hi> by fire, to a <hi>preſervation</hi> in fire, from a temporall to an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall burning? Yet in all this <hi>Moſes</hi> having declared the author God, the cauſe their ſin, <hi>Aaron</hi> was dumb and held his peace: It was not ſuch a dumbneſs as <hi>Zachary</hi> had; that was <hi>poenal,</hi> &amp; unbelief ſtruck him dumb; this was a ſpirituall dumbneſs, and faith ſtruck him dumb, it did not ſo much ſuſpend his tongue from ſpeaking, as ſilence his heart from complaining, and made him quietly ſubmit to God's dealing.</p>
            <p>Thus having at once ſhewed you both the parts of the Text, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97618:11"/>cleared what ever had any appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing difficulty in it,
<note place="margin">Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> we will now lay down the ſeverall concluſions the Text affords us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That they who have to do with any Ordinance of God, draw neer to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That they who draw neer to God in any Ordinance, muſt ſanctifie God in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That if wee do not ſanctifie God in an Ordinance, hee will be ſanctified upon us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We will ſpeak a little of the firſt, which is an <hi>Introduction</hi> to thoſe which follow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That they who have to do with any Ordinance of God, draw neer to God.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee it is the <hi>language</hi> of the Spirit of God here, that to have to do with any <hi>matter</hi> which concerns the <hi>Worſhip</hi> and ſervice of God, is, <hi>do draw neer to God.</hi> And in other places it is cal'd <hi>a coming before God, a treading his Courts, an approaching</hi> to God, <hi>a meeting</hi> of God; all which languages imply thus much, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97618:12"/>who ever have to do with God in any Ordinance, draw neer to God. You <hi>tread</hi> his Courts, you <hi>come</hi> into his preſence, you <hi>approach</hi> unto God, you <hi>meet</hi> God, you have <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> with God; Nay, you have to do with God's <hi>Name;</hi> God's <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi> are <hi>part</hi> of his <hi>Name.</hi> Nay, you have to doe with <hi>God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> Hee that hath to doe with any Ordinance, with any part of his Worſhip, hath to do with <hi>God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> When you have to do with the Word, when you go to Prayer, when you have to do with the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, you have to do with <hi>God himſelf</hi> in them. What could the <hi>Word</hi> do, either in <hi>commands</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage us, in <hi>Promiſes</hi> to comfort us, in <hi>threatenings</hi> to terrifie us, if wee had not to <hi>do</hi> with God in them? What were <hi>Prayer,</hi> but a diſtracted ſeriouſneſs, a religious madneſs, if we had not to deal with God in it? What were the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> but gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97618:12"/>Pageants, nay, empty fantaſies, beggerly elements, if we had not to deal with God in them?</p>
            <p>It is God that wee have to <hi>deal</hi> withall in Ordinances, that <hi>ſheds</hi> a glory, <hi>caſts</hi> a Majeſty, and <hi>puts an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie</hi> into all the Ordinances we have to deal withall: It is hee who makes the <hi>Promiſes</hi> of the Word <hi>rocks</hi> of ſtay and ſupport, that makes the <hi>commands</hi> of the Word full of <hi>authority,</hi> that makes the <hi>threatnings</hi> of the Word exceeding terrible; It is he that we have to deal withall, that makes a little <hi>handfull</hi> of water, a little <hi>bit</hi> of bread, and <hi>ſup</hi> of wine, exceeding <hi>glorious</hi> and efficacious. What empty, what poor, what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptible things would theſe be (and are to unbelieving men) if wee had not to do with God in them? It is this God we have to do withall, that caſts a Majeſty upon, and puts an efficacy into every Ordinance.</p>
            <p>But we will paſs over this. If they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97618:13"/>who have to do w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> any Ordinance of God, <hi>draw neer to God,</hi> then let me put ſome things to you to judge of.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Judge then, if ever <hi>Kingdom</hi> was more <hi>ingaged</hi> to God then ours, who injoy the <hi>Ordinances</hi> by which we draw neer to God. Hath he dealt thus with any Nation? What Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion under heaven that enjoy the like priviledges of drawing neere to God in Ordinances as we doe? Well may we ſay in the words of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.5. <hi>Bleſſed is the Nation which thou chuſeſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 65.5.</note> 
               <hi>and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt to approach unto thee, that they may dwell in thy Courts, we ſhall be ſatisfied with the goodneſſe</hi> of thy houſe, <hi>even of thy holy Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And with bleſſing God for our owne priviledges, judge what cauſe we have to take up a lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for them that never enjoyed; &amp; for them who have enjoyed, but are now deprived of this means of drawing neere to God.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:97618:13"/>1. Them who <hi>never enjoyed</hi> the Ordinances, who ſit in <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> and in the ſhadow of death, who <hi>never</hi> had a <hi>Chriſt,</hi> a Goſpel <hi>diſcovered</hi> to them. Oh, pity and pray for them, that the <hi>Word</hi> of the Lord might <hi>run</hi> &amp; be glorified, that God would <hi>inlarge</hi> the <hi>bounds</hi> of his ſanctuary, ſtretch forth the <hi>Curtains</hi> of his Tabernacle, that the <hi>eyes</hi> of Nations might be opened, that the <hi>fulneſs</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> might be brought in, &amp; that they might flie to the Church as <hi>Doves into the windows,</hi> which is propheſied, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.8. And w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> them, Oh, remember that <hi>antient nation,</hi> the <hi>Jews,</hi> who have drawn neere to God in Ordinances, but now at diſtance with him, and even ſet at <hi>further</hi> diſtance by the uſe of thoſe Ordinances, whereby <hi>formerly</hi> they drew neer; Oh remember them! that that blood which they impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated upon themſelves for a <hi>curſe,</hi> may now be upon them for a <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:97618:14"/>that it may lie no longer upon their <hi>heads,</hi> but now be <hi>ſprinkled</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their <hi>hearts,</hi> and be <hi>in veniam</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> hath been ſo long <hi>in vindictam;</hi> That as it was ſaid of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſo it may now be ſaid of the <hi>Jewes, That unto them is granted repentance to life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And take up a mourning for them who have <hi>injoyed</hi> the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, but now <hi>want</hi> them; look into <hi>Germany,</hi> look into <hi>Ireland,</hi> nay look into many places in <hi>England,</hi> how many <hi>Paſtors,</hi> who are driven away from their flocks, how many <hi>Shepheards</hi> ſmitten, and the <hi>ſheep</hi> ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, how many poor <hi>ſcattered flocks,</hi> who had the Manna fell at their tent doors, &amp; their <hi>tents</hi> about the Tabernacle, who now have the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> removed, are without Word, without Sacraments, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Ordinances, and are forced to <hi>wander</hi> from place to place, to <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of the <hi>bread</hi> of heaven, to injoy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97618:14"/>the Ordinances whereby they may draw neer to God?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Judge then, if it be not a <hi>vile thing,</hi> to hinder &amp; <hi>diſturb</hi> the Saints in thoſe things whereby they draw neer to God. 1. Either by <hi>depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them</hi> of Ordinances, and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing them of the means: 2. Or by <hi>corrupting</hi> of the Ordinances to them, that they cannot injoy them in that <hi>purity</hi> which God left them. In the firſt, the bread is <hi>taken</hi> from them: In the ſecond, they give them <hi>poyſon</hi> with their bread; both theſe will have a <hi>ſad</hi> day of rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning.</p>
            <p n="4">4. See what's the reaſon the Saints are ſo much <hi>taken</hi> with Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, becauſe they <hi>draw neer</hi> to God in them; they look upon Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances as <hi>Bridges</hi> to give them a paſſage to God; as <hi>Boats</hi> to convey them into the <hi>boſome</hi> of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Vehicula Spiritus.</note> as means to bring them into more <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate communion</hi> with their Father,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97618:15"/>therfore are they ſo much taken w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> them. When they go to the <hi>Word,</hi> they go as one goes to hear <hi>news</hi> of a friend; when they go to <hi>pray,</hi> they go to <hi>talk</hi> with a friend; when to <hi>read,</hi> they go to reade a <hi>letter</hi> from a friend; when to <hi>receive,</hi> they go to <hi>ſup</hi> with a friend: they look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Ordinances as thoſe things whereby they have to do with God, and therfore are ordinances ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious. Indeed to them who have to <hi>do</hi> with <hi>nothing</hi> but <hi>duty,</hi> in <hi>duty,</hi> but <hi>prayer,</hi> in <hi>prayer,</hi> but <hi>hearing,</hi> in <hi>hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> to them the Ordinances are dead, dry, and ſpiritleſs things, but they who have to <hi>do</hi> with God in duty, they who have <hi>communion</hi> with God in Ordinances, to them Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances are paſſing ſweet and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Judge what cauſe there is to <hi>keep</hi> our hearts in a ſpirituall and holy frame; wee have often to do with Ordinances, and when we have
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97618:15"/>to do with Ordinances, we have to do with God, we draw neer to him. And therefore, what cauſe to get and keep our hearts in a holy tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, that we may be ever fit to cloſe with God in them, and not have our hearts like <hi>bad ſervants,</hi> to ſeek when we are to uſe them. The Apoſtle bids us <hi>pray continually,</hi> it is not meant that wee are ever to be upon our knees, ever in <hi>actuall</hi> prayer, but ſeeing we are to pray ſo frequently, we are to get and keep our hearts in ſuch an habituall frame and diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they may be ever fit to <hi>cloſe</hi> with God, when ever wee are called out upon the duty.</p>
            <p>Were wee but ſeldom to have to do with God, you might think there were no ſuch need of keeping our hearts in frame; but ſeeing we are to do with him <hi>daily,</hi> who is ſo pure and holy a God, <hi>Oh, what manner of perſons ought we to be?</hi> How exactly ſhould we walk? <hi>Jerem.</hi> 7.9.10. <hi>Will
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97618:16"/>you ſteal and murther, and come and ſtand before mee in this houſe which is called by my name,</hi> ſaith the Lord? ſo will you walk looſly, live vainly, when you are to do with ſo holy a God every day? Oh, let every man that <hi>calls upon the name of the Lord, depart from iniquity.</hi> Let every one that holds up praying duties, keep his heart in a praying frame: ſuch a Chriſtian is not worth a pin, who is only good when he is on his knees, who thinks it ſufficient to ſnatch up affections to ſerve the turne of a duty, and then to lay them aſide as ſoone as the duty is over: hee is a Chriſtian indeed who prays on his <hi>feet</hi> as well as on his <hi>knees,</hi> whoſe life is nothing elſe but a <hi>reall prayer,</hi> that if you look into his heart, there is all his <hi>deſires</hi> ingraven, his heart ever pants and breaths the ſame things he prayes; and if you look into his life, his <hi>life</hi> ſpeaks the ſame language his <hi>lips</hi> do; his life is a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97618:16"/>
               <hi>walking prayer;</hi> many men are <hi>one</hi> upon their knees, <hi>another</hi> upon their feet, but he is the ſame; hee walks with the ſame ſpirit, the ſame affections, the ſame deſires and diſpoſition: hee is the ſame man. It is <hi>ſomething</hi> to pray, <hi>more</hi> to pray as a Chriſtian, and <hi>more</hi> when you have prayed your prayers, to <hi>live</hi> your prayers; nay, to live thoſe affections, thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions wherewith you prayed, to live as high as prayer. It is a ſhame to ſee, how we <hi>ſlide</hi> out of duty into the world, and out of the <hi>world</hi> into duty again; as if we were two contrary men, one up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our knees, and another on our feet: And therefore you ſhall ſee men to <hi>gather</hi> up ſome affections, ſome diſpoſitions, before they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on a duty, and <hi>put themſelves</hi> into <hi>another</hi> frame; but lay them <hi>aſide</hi> as ſoon as ever they have done; theſe muſt only ſerve to <hi>act</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:97618:17"/>a praying part, when that is done, then lay them aſide; you have no more <hi>uſe</hi> of them, you muſt put on another ſpirit to go into the world withall. Chriſtians, you have often to <hi>do</hi> with Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and had therefore need to <hi>keep</hi> your hearts in an Ordinance frame: hee who keeps not <hi>cloſe</hi> to God in <hi>practice,</hi> ſhall never keep <hi>cloſe</hi> to God in prayer; <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> in life breeds <hi>diſtance</hi> in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And what need of keeping up praying affections? what a ſhame to have our <hi>lives</hi> give our <hi>lips</hi> the lye, our practice be a <hi>confutation</hi> of our prayers? In our <hi>prayer</hi> to be warm, in our <hi>practice</hi> cold, <hi>up</hi> in duty, <hi>down</hi> in life? Oh learn to live as <hi>high</hi> as duty; thou never prayeſt indeed, till thy practice come up as <hi>high</hi> as thy prayers, till thou loves <hi>confeſsions,</hi> and art humble, thou loves <hi>petitions</hi> and art thirſty, and diligent for thoſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97618:17"/>things thou begs, till a man may reade by thy life, that thou art one who deſireſt thoſe things, which thou haſt uttered with thy lips. Let this frame of ſpirit be in your <hi>eye</hi> to aim at, and in your <hi>life</hi> to indeavour after. — But I am too large, I intended this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine only for the porch or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance to the reſt. To draw there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore up to the concluſion of it.</p>
            <p n="1">I. If it be ſo, that who ever hath to do with an Ordinance, hath to do with God in it, hee draws neer to God; Let me then exhort you:
<list>
                  <item>1. To a <hi>conſcionable</hi> uſe of Ordinances.</item>
                  <item>2. To <hi>conſcionableneſse</hi> in the uſe of them.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Let me exhort you to a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable</hi> uſe of Ordinances. Be more frequent in hearing, in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in receiving, &amp;c.— I might ſay ſomething to this laſt, <hi>viz. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:97618:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>The Apoſtle tells us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. <hi>As often as wee eat this bread, wee ſhew forth the Lord's death;</hi> it implies a <hi>frequent</hi> uſe of the Ordinance, more then once or twice a year, or once a quarter. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the opportunities might be more frequent, if it were not for the coldneſs and deadneſs of our hearts. In the <hi>Primitive</hi> times of the Church, while the <hi>blood</hi> of Chriſt was <hi>warm,</hi> they had the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament every day; wee have an uncontradicted authority, that they had it every <hi>Lord's day.</hi> And as men <hi>grew</hi> colder, ſo the <hi>diſtances</hi> grew greater. Sure, were it not for the coldneſs and deadneſs of our hearts, it might almoſt be our <hi>daily bread;</hi> at leaſt wee might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy a more frequent uſe of this Ordinance then we do: but as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>as oft as you have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity do good:</hi> ſo as oft as you have the opportunity, take the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97618:18"/>to meet God in his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By them you ſee you draw neer to God, you come into his preſence, you have to do with God's Name; nay, you have to do with God himſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By them God draws neer to you, he walks among the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticks, he preſents himſelf in his Ordinances; <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.1. and there he directs us to finde him; <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.7, 8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If wee keep not up a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable uſe of Ordinances, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance will grow between God and you: As the Water-man may loſe more by the omiſſion of one ſtroke then he is able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover again by many; ſo may you loſe more by the omiſſion of one duty, then you are able to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver again by the <hi>performance</hi> of many; eſpecially, if this omiſſion hath ariſen, 1. from neglect of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97618:19"/>God: 2. from careleſneſs: 3. from ſleighting of the converſes with God: 4. or from the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and ſolicitations of Satan and our corruptions: 5. or, from the blandiſhments of the world: If upon ſuch grounds, little doſt thou know what thou loſeſt by ſuch an omiſſion. If notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all indeavours, it be ſo hard to keep communion with God, what would it be, if we ſhould caſt up our Oars, and neglect it whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? You ſee what a diſtance was bred between God &amp; <hi>Iſrael, Jer.</hi> 2. And what was the ground of it? why, ſaith the Text, <hi>My people have forgotten mee dayes without number;</hi> they had no care to keep and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion and acquaintance with him, and ſo diſtances were bred between God and them: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect of duty breeds ſtrangeneſs, ſtrangeneſs diſtance, diſtance fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off. A good caveat in theſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97618:19"/>dayes, when ſo many do cry down duty; ſhall we look upon that as our <hi>burthen,</hi> which is our <hi>glory;</hi> our <hi>bondage,</hi> which is our <hi>priviledge?</hi> what is the <hi>happineſs</hi> of a glorified Saint, but only that he is alwayes under the <hi>line</hi> of love, ever in the contemplation, and converſes with God? And ſhall that be thought our <hi>burthen</hi> here w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is our <hi>glory</hi> hereafter? By this, firſt, you come to ſee the face of God: ſecondly, you have converſes with him: thirdly, you get new quicken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: fourthly, new incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: fifthly, freſh ſtrength a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin: ſixthly, new ſupplies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the temptations of <hi>Satan</hi> &amp; the <hi>world:</hi> ſeventhly, freſh ſtrength to walk with God: eighthly, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor againſt our luſts; and this is enough to make us conſcionable.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We know not how ſoon we may be deprived of Ordinances; wee have <hi>play'd</hi> with the breaſts,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97618:20"/>and God might put them up; we have <hi>ſinn'd</hi> in the light, and God might <hi>put</hi> out our light. How juſtly might God <hi>remove</hi> his Candleſticks, let out his <hi>Vineyard</hi> to other Husbandmen, and ſeek for other <hi>ground</hi> to ſow the ſeed of his Ordinances upon; ſeeing the <hi>ground</hi> where it hath been <hi>ſown</hi> hath brought forth ſo little fruit, how deſervedly might hee ſuffer us to wiſh and wander to injoy one of the days of the Son of man which we have injoyed?</p>
            <p>But though God do not take away the Ordinances from us, yet hee may <hi>take</hi> us from the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and that not only by death, but in life it ſelf; and a ſad thought this will bring to thy ſoul, when conſcience ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to you, your former negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in the uſe of Ordinances.—</p>
            <p n="2">II. Let me exhort you not only to a conſcionable uſe of ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97618:20"/>but to <hi>Conſcionableneſs</hi> in the uſe of them; be not onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable to uſe them, but let your hearts be wrought up to a <hi>Conſcionableneſſe</hi> in the uſe of them. The <hi>power</hi> of the Word, the <hi>terror</hi> of the Law, the <hi>fear</hi> of wrath, and the <hi>hope</hi> of reward, may put a man to do duty; yea, &amp; have power upon the ſpirit, and ingage the conſcience to doe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: You ſee many that <hi>dare not</hi> but pray, and yet have <hi>no heart</hi> in prayer; they have a <hi>conſcience</hi> to doe duty, but their hearts are not brought to any <hi>conſcientiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> in the doing of it. A com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon work of God, may make men conſcionable to doe many duties, but nothing but the <hi>Spirit and Grace</hi> of Chriſt, will work up the heart to a conſcionableneſſe in the doing of them.</p>
            <p>To this conſcionableneſſe in the performance of Ordinances,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97618:21"/>would I exhort you upon this <hi>ground,</hi> becauſe you draw neere to God, have to doe with him. And as in all, ſo in particular in this Ordinance of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe otherwiſe ye get no good: 1. no good of Grace, no improvement of Holineſſe: 2. Nor no good of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> comes not in from the bare <hi>doing</hi> of the duty, but from the <hi>manner</hi> of doing, it is not the <hi>iſſue</hi> of <hi>conſcience</hi> to doe, but of conſcionableneſſe in the doing of them. All the <hi>Sermons</hi> you have heard, all the <hi>Prayers</hi> you have prayd, all the <hi>Sacraments</hi> you have received, though done <hi>out of conſcience,</hi> as you ſay, will not miniſter one dram of true <hi>comfort</hi> to you upon your death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beds, if your ſpirits have not been wrought up to a <hi>conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe</hi> in the doing of them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:97618:21"/>2. Becauſe otherwiſe you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke God; to give him the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſe and out-ſide of duty, and to with-hold the <hi>life and ſpirit</hi> of duty, is a provocation of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe otherwiſe you will <hi>contract</hi> much <hi>guilt,</hi> and bring much evill upon your own ſouls. This is ſure, that Ordinances u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in an unconſcionable way, 1. They give Satan further poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of us. 2. They put much weight to our ſin. 3. They ſet our ſoules at further diſtance with God. 4. They ripen us to the great downfall, the great ſin lies among ſuch. 5. They make our conditions more irrecove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. When a man comes to be Ordinance-proofe, prayer-proof, Sermon and Sacrament-proofe, that none of theſe can enter and work upon him, he is out-grown the power of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, that man's condition is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97618:22"/>very neere deſperate.</p>
            <p>There is nothing makes the condition of the ſoule more <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate</hi> and unrecoverable, then the uſe of Ordinances in a <hi>formall</hi> and unconſcionable way, when a man doth <hi>harden</hi> under means of ſoftning. When a mans ſoar runs under the plaiſter, nay when the plaiſter increaſeth the ſoar; when that which ſhould draw us neere, ſets us at fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtance; this man's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is dangerous. Scarce one of many are ever wrought upon: When once a man can heare and pray, and receive, and yet <hi>retaine</hi> his ſinne too without diſturbance, all this doth not trouble him, no weapon will pierce him; no command, no threatning of the Word, no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Ordinances can move him: this man is in great danger to <hi>die</hi> in this condition. And the uſe of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97618:22"/>Ordinances in a formall way, brings men to ſuch a condition. As the uſe of <hi>Phyſick</hi> in an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary way, doth take away the working of it; ſo the uſe of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances</hi> in a <hi>formall</hi> way, doth take off the edge, and blunt the power of working on the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Well then, let me exhort you not onely to be conſcionable to uſe, but to a conſcionableneſſe in the uſe of this ordinance. And this lies in two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That you come with hearts habitually diſpoſed: which lies alſo in two things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. To be brought out of a ſtate of ſin; 1. the power, 2. practiſe, 3. love of all ſin: for Sin ſets a <hi>diſtance</hi> between you and God in ordinances, it <hi>pollutes</hi> an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, it <hi>indiſpoſeth</hi> you for acceptance in it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To be brought into a ſtate of grace, to have your natures
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97618:23"/>changed, not partially, but uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally &amp; ſpiritually, not only to have new practices, but new princples. <hi>Old things paſt away, and all things become new.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This conſcionablenes in the uſe of Ordinances, it lies in this, That you come with hearts actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally diſpoſed, and that conſiſts in two things,
<list>
                  <item>1. Examination.</item>
                  <item>2. Excitation.</item>
               </list> But of theſe I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak larger in the following diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>There is yet another branch of the exhortation.</p>
            <p>If ſo be that whoever hath to doe with any Ordinance of God, hath to doe with God in it; Oh then when ever you goe to have to doe with any Ordinance, be ſure you <hi>take Chriſt</hi> with you. There is a neceſſitie of this,
<list>
                  <item>1. In regard of <hi>Admiſsion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. In regard of <hi>Aſsiſtance.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. In regard of <hi>Acceptance.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:97618:23"/>1. In regard of <hi>Admiſsion,</hi> God is a conſuming fire, and we are but dried ſtubble, there is no ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching of him but in Chriſt, in whom we may have acceſs with boldneſſe to the throne of grace; God will not look pleaſingly on you, if you come without Chriſt, here is no throne of grace with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him; without Chriſt it is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Barre or <hi>Tribunall</hi> of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, then a <hi>Throne</hi> of Grace.
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 12. Heb. 14.14, 16. Heb. 10.12.23.</note> It is Chriſt who makes that which was a <hi>Barre of juſtice,</hi> a <hi>Bench of mercie.</hi> In him we have admiſſion. You goe upon this Ordinance now, but goe not in the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of your preparations, but in the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of Chriſt. Say, Lord I come alone in the <hi>Merits</hi> of Chriſt, to partake of the <hi>Merits</hi> of the Lord Jeſus. I come in the <hi>blood</hi> of Chriſt, to partake of the <hi>blood</hi> of the Lord Jeſus. I have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devoured to prepare and fit my
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97618:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:97618:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:97618:25"/>ſelf through thy grace, but I look not for admiſſion through my preparations, but through the blood and mediation of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. There is a neceſſitie of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in regard of <hi>Aſsiſtance:</hi> You go upon Ordinances, but you have no ſtrength to do them without Chriſt, who is ſufficient for theſe things? you might as well bee ſet to <hi>move Mountains,</hi> as to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake Ordinances, without the ſtrength of Chriſt, <hi>without me you can doe nothing,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. without <hi>Union</hi> with him, without <hi>Communion</hi> with him: from him we muſt have both <hi>ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perating</hi> and <hi>cooperating</hi> ſtrength, both <hi>inherent</hi> &amp; <hi>adſiſtent</hi> ſtrength, otherwiſe though you have grace, yet you will not bee able to performe any worke, nor exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe your owne graces. It is hee that muſt work all our works in us, and for us; the <hi>inherent</hi> work
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97618:25"/>of grace <hi>within</hi> us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quodà me requiris ipſe donaſti prius.</hi> Chryſoſt.</note> and the <hi>requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> works of duty for us. And bleſſed be that God, who hath given to us what he requireth of us, and hath not only made Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts promiſes, but made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, performances.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is a neceſſity of Chriſt in regard of <hi>acceptance.</hi> Our works,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nihil ab ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine exit quamvis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecto quod non ſit aliquae macula in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinatum.</hi> Calvin.</note> they are not only impotent, but impure too, as they come from us. It is Chriſt that muſt put validity to them, and Chriſt that muſt put his own <hi>odours</hi> to them; Chriſt muſt put both his ſpirit &amp;
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Meritu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um miſeratio Domini, non ſum planè meriti inops quandiu non fuerit il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ops miſeratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne meminero juſtitiae tuae ſolius, ipſa enim eſt &amp; mea, &amp;c.</hi> Calv. <hi>Inſtit. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 120. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</note> merit to them, his <hi>Grace</hi> to work them, and his <hi>blood</hi> to own them; what ever comes from his <hi>Spirit,</hi> is preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted through his <hi>Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here is a great comfort; thou looks over thy performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and canſt not ſee, how ever God can accept them: ſo much deadneſs, ſo little life, ſo much
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97618:26"/>coldneſs;
<note place="margin">God looks not on the works of the Saints, <hi>In foro ſtricti ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> but <hi>in foro Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelii.</hi> Eph. 1.6.</note> But God looks upon them not as <hi>thine,</hi> but as Chriſts, in whom not only our perſons, but our performances are accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Chriſt gives us his Spirit, and Chriſt is willing to own what we preſent by his Spirit, and God is willing to own what ever is preſented to him by his Son.</p>
            <p>Well then, thou haſt to do with the Ordinances of God, by theſe thou draws neer to God; but would you be admitted into the preſence of God? would you have God to hold out a golden Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to you? would you have grace and aſſiſtance to perform the work? would you have acceptance when the work is done? Oh get <hi>Chriſt</hi> to go along with you! And thus much for the firſt Doctrine, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is an introduction to the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That they who draw neer to God in any ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> muſt ſanctifie God in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In proſecution of which, wee ſhal do three things: we wil ſhew,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:97618:26"/>1. <hi>What it is to ſanctifie God</hi> in an Ordinance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>How we muſt ſanctifie God</hi> in an Ordinance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Why we muſt ſanctifie God</hi> in an ordinance. And ſo to application.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>What it is to ſanctifie God in an Ordinance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the ſanctifying of God in an Ordinance, there is ſomething required,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>In the work.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>In the workman.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The work,</hi> and that is, that it be an ordinance, ſuch a one as he himſelf hath inſtituted and ſet up, otherwiſe wee cannot ſanctifie God in it, no more then the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in their blind devotions and ſuperſtitions. Theſe offer <hi>ſtrange fire.</hi> As God's <hi>Benediction</hi> doth not accompany any thing further then 'tis an Ordinance of his, ſo our <hi>ſanctification</hi> of God extends no further then to his own ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, which he himſelf hath ſet
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97618:27"/>up &amp; ordained; in other things we <hi>ſanctifie</hi> him not, we <hi>diſhonor</hi> him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Something required <hi>in the workman:</hi> To ſay nothing here of the main requiſite, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is, that hee be in Chriſt: for that we take hee be in Chriſt: for that we take for granted; &amp; to qualifie ſuch a one to this ordinance: and in ſuch a one there is ſomething required in his head, ſomthing in his heart.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>In his head,</hi> and that is, firſt, that hee <hi>conceive</hi> aright of God: ſecondly, and that he <hi>conceive</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right of the ordinance. 1. That he <hi>conceive</hi> aright of God, that he hath a right knowledge of God, right conceptions of God in his Nature, in his Perſon, in his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itrbutes, Son. 2. Of his Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, 1. in the nature of them, 2. the uſe of them, 3. the fruit and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Somthing in his heart;</hi> and that,</p>
            <p>Firſt, that hee bring <hi>holy affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> to it; every ordinance of God
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97618:27"/>requires the affections to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about it, and not only af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, but holy affections, ſuch affections as do ariſe from a holy heart; there is the ſpring. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound profeſſours may ſometime have ſome <hi>flaſhings</hi> in their devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as you ſee <hi>Herod,</hi> who heard <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> joyfully; they may have ſome affections, but: 1. They are not <hi>holy</hi> affections: 2. Not ſuch as ariſe from a <hi>principle,</hi> a ſpring within, there's no root: 3. They are not <hi>orderly</hi> affections, they break out before knowledge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore faith: 4. They are not <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> affections, but land-flouds, for a time: 5. They are not <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming</hi> affections, ſuch as change the heart; and therefore ſuch af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections may be exerciſed, yet they leave a man as they found him, and ſuch a man cannot ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie God in an <hi>Ordinance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, there muſt not only
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97618:28"/>be <hi>holy affections,</hi> but ſuch as are <hi>ſutable</hi> to the Ordinance &amp; Work in hand. It is poſſible to have <hi>holy affections,</hi> them <hi>ſtirred</hi> up in an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and yet not <hi>ſanctifie</hi> God in it, becauſe theſe are not <hi>ſutable</hi> to the Ordinance, <hi>Nihil ad rem,</hi> nothing to the work in hand; they ſute not with the preſent ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance that God hath called the ſoul out upon, as I could ſhew you at large.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, there muſt not only be <hi>holy affections</hi> and ſutable affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, but thoſe <hi>excited</hi> and <hi>ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> up. A man may have <hi>holy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,</hi> and ſuch as are ſutable to an <hi>Ordinance,</hi> as the Saints have in the frame of Grace, and yet not ſanctifie God in an <hi>Ordinance,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not excited and ſtirred up:
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.6 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſignif. ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m ſopi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum &amp; ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem cineri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum folle aut flatu ſuſcitare, ut reardeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat.</hi> Paſſer.</note> 
               <hi>Stir up the gift of God in thee,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle to <hi>Timothy;</hi> that is, excite and blow up the gifts and <hi>graces</hi> of God in thee.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:97618:28"/>
            <p>When you are to do with God, you muſt <hi>ſtir up</hi> thoſe affections, and graces which are within you. And this requires a matter of pains; <hi>affections</hi> are not ever at hand, nor ever at command; a man hath not his <hi>heart</hi> under lock and key. And therefore God in mercy conſidering and reſpecting our weakneſs, hath graciouſly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted a time of <hi>preparation,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he call us forth upon the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance</hi> of an <hi>Ordinance,</hi> that ſo we might get our <hi>affections</hi> up, our hearts in tune. Once indeed wee reade, that men were called out upon an ordinance, and were <hi>ſtraitned</hi> with time to prepare themſelves according to the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration</hi> of the Sanctuary, as in <hi>Hezekiah's</hi> time.
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 30.18.19.</note> They had <hi>habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall</hi> preparation, but wanted <hi>actuall;</hi> and in that caſe, the want of time, God pardoned it, but it was <hi>prayed</hi> for, it was ſought
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97618:29"/>for, and ſought for <hi>earneſtly.</hi> But we read another time, that God puniſhed the want of this <hi>actuall</hi> preparation, and ſtirring up their graces &amp; affections; yea, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed it <hi>ſeverely,</hi> with the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſickneſſe, death of many of the Corinthians. <hi>For this cauſe many are ſick, many are weak, many are fallen aſleep;</hi> yet were they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitually prepared; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1.</p>
            <p>God takes it for a great <hi>diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> to him, that we ſhould come ſlightly on ſo great a worke, to which all the affections we have, and all the affections we can ſtir up, are little enough. Wee had need call in for all the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of grace, nay all the <hi>ſuccours</hi> in Chriſt, and all the <hi>ſupplies</hi> and aids of the Spirit to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it. By this you may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what it is to ſanctifie God in an Ordinance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How muſt wee ſanctifie God in an Ordinance?</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:97618:29"/>
            <p>To ſanctify God in an ordinance, there is required ſomething
<list>
                  <item>1. Antecedent.</item>
                  <item>2. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>comitant</item>
                  <item>3. Subſequent.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Somthing Antecedent, or before.</hi> 2. <hi>Somthing in the time.</hi> 3. <hi>After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</hi> Theſe are generals, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to every particular Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as I could ſhew you at large.
<note place="margin">In hearing the Word.</note>
            </p>
            <p>When you come to heare the word, there is ſomthing required before, as 1. <hi>Meditation,</hi> into what place, into whoſe preſence, about what buſineſſe we goe. 2. <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination</hi> of 1. <hi>our ſins,</hi> that here we might have them ſlain by the ſword of the Spirit in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the word. 2. <hi>Our graces,</hi> that here wee might have them ſtrengthened and nouriſhed by the ſpirituall food of our ſoules. 3. <hi>Prayer</hi> for the Miniſter, for the Congregation, our ſelves, that a bleſſing may be upon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In the time</hi> is required, 1. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:97618:30"/>2. <hi>Attention,</hi> 3. <hi>Submiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of ſpirit and <hi>humility.</hi> 4. <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Afterward, Prayer</hi> again, which muſt be the Alpha and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mega, 2. <hi>Meditation,</hi> 3. <hi>fruitfulneſs,</hi> and <hi>obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So for Prayer, there is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<note place="margin">Prayer.</note> 1. Before, <hi>Meditation, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi> 2. <hi>In the time, faith, fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vencie, humility,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ex radic.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ordinavit, aciem diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſuit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſutableneſſe</hi> of ſpirit, <hi>inlarged deſires.</hi> 3. <hi>After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſuch a deportment and demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> as is ſutable to ſuch who call upon God, as <hi>to depart from ſin, to apply our hearts to obedience, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the anſwer and return of our Prayers.</hi> Pſal. 5.3. <hi>In the morning I will direct my prayer,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ex radic.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Speculando expectavit hinc</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſpeculator.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and look up.</hi> There are two military words, he would not only pray, but mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall up his prayers, put them in array; and when he had done, hee would be as a Spie upon a tower, to ſee whether he prevailed, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he got the day.</p>
            <p>But to paſſe theſe, &amp; come to the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97618:30"/>Ordinance we are to enter upon, the Sacrament.
<note place="margin">Sacrament</note> To ſanctifie God in which, there is required, 1. ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing before, 2. ſomthing in the time, and 3. ſomething after.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Something before,</hi> which may be laid down in theſe two heads,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Habituall,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Actuall.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Habituall preparation,</hi> which doth conſiſt in the whole frame of grace and ſanctification. It is an ordinance onely for ſuch who are ſanctified, we are to have, 1. <hi>A ſaving knowledge</hi> of God, of our ſelves, 2. <hi>lively faith,</hi> 3. <hi>a true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> 4. <hi>love,</hi> 5. <hi>hunger and thirſt</hi> after Chriſt: this is a feaſt, and no comming without ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach. 6. <hi>Thankfulneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Actuall preparation,</hi> and that conſiſts in the actuall ſtirring up and exciting of thoſe graces which are in you. There muſt be a new exciting of faith, a new ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of repentance, the latitude
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97618:31"/>and extent whereof is for all ſin, but eſpecially for thoſe ſinnes which you have committed ſince the laſt time you renewed your covenant with God, in this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. So a ſtirring up of our love, affections, our deſires, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, thirſt. This is required before, which becauſe it is ſo largely treated upon,
<note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Dike</hi> on the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam.</hi>
               </note> by many learned and godly Divines, I ſhall purpoſely wave any further trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it, referring you in this point to what they have ſo large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly written.</p>
            <p>Paſſing this therefore, we fall upon the ſecond, which hath not been ſo frequently taught.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As there is ſomething then required before, <hi>viz.</hi> Habituall and actuall preparation: ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly <hi>there is ſomething required in the time;</hi> and that is the <hi>exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe</hi> of <hi>Graces,</hi> and gracions diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions. A man may be a ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97618:31"/>perſon, and yet not ſanctifie God in this Ordinance, if he doe not <hi>exerciſe</hi> thoſe <hi>Graces,</hi> &amp; graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſpoſitions w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth here, &amp; are <hi>ſutable</hi> to the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and nature of the Ordinance.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Now the firſt and great grace that here is to be exerciſed, is <hi>Faith. Faith</hi> is the great Grace which gives admiſſion unto this ordinance, and faith is the great grace that is to be exerciſed, and to run through the uſe of it.</p>
            <p>Concerning which we ſhall deſire to unfold three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>What act of Faith is here to be exerciſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Upon what object we muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe our Faith here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>For what benefits faith muſt here be exerciſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> what act of <hi>Faith</hi> is here to bee exerciſed. There are theſe two main <hi>acts</hi> of Faith. 1. An act of <hi>Recumbence:</hi> 2. An act of <hi>apprehenſion</hi> &amp; appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97618:32"/>of Chriſt.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fides po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt habere aliquem modum du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitationis ſalvâ fide.</hi> Daven. <hi>Fideicerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portat fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatem adhaeſionis, non quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationem intellectus.</hi> Aquin.</note> Both theſe may be exerciſed here, and to our <hi>ſpirituall</hi> benefit.</p>
            <p>By the one we <hi>go over</hi> to Chriſt, by the other we bring Chriſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to us.</p>
            <p>The firſt act of <hi>Faith</hi> gives us an intereſt in all the benefits of Chriſt, though as yet the ſoule is not able to bring home to it ſelfe the great <hi>revenue</hi> of mercie and grace, which Chriſt hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed, and the ſoule hath an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in. The ſecond act of faith brings it all home. In the former God makes Chriſt ours, and we his; in the latter wee make him ours. Chriſt in his <hi>blood</hi> and <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> Chriſt in his <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> Chriſt in all his <hi>doings</hi> and <hi>ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings;</hi> ſo far as he is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municable to poore ſinners. Now there is not much difference betweene theſe two acts. The difference is not in the <hi>nature</hi> and eſſence of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97618:32"/>the grace, both are faith and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving faith; nor in the fruits and benefits, both <hi>give</hi> a man <hi>union</hi> and communion with Chriſt, &amp;c. But the difference is in the <hi>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures</hi> and degrees, in the comforts of it. To the firſt there goes a conviction of ſin, a manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and clearing of the promiſe, a perſwaſion of the truth, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, freeneſſe, ſutableneſſe, and goodneſſe of the promiſe. And upon all this here is a rowling, a reſting upon Chriſt. And the latter is but a further degree, a bringing over or home all this to its own ſelfe. In the <hi>former act</hi> the ſoule hath communion with all the benefits of Chriſt. It's ſuch an act of Faith, as gives a ſoule union with the perſon, and that cannot be without commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the priviledges and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits. In this latter there is but a <hi>clearer apprehenſion</hi> of it. In the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97618:33"/>firſt we go over to Chriſt: in the latter we bring over Chriſt to us. In the former we are <hi>apprehended</hi> of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.12.</note> in the latter wee <hi>appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend</hi> Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now, to the Anſwer, what act of faith is here to be exerciſed: unto which I ſay, that that act of faith which doth apprehend and apply Chriſt, is moſt ſutable to this ordinance of the Sacrament; hence is this called a <hi>taking</hi> of Chriſt, a <hi>receiving</hi> of Chriſt, a <hi>feeding</hi> upon Chriſt, <hi>eating</hi> his fleſh, and <hi>drinking</hi> his blood; all which ſhew this act is moſt ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the ordinance.</p>
            <p>Here we have an <hi>offer</hi> of Chriſt, and this act is moſt ſutable to <hi>take</hi> him as offered. And the more ſtrength wee have to apply and bring Chriſt home, the more we <hi>feed</hi> on him, the more wee are nouriſhed, and built up.</p>
            <p>But though this act of faith is
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97618:33"/>moſt ſutable to the ordinance, yet wee ſhut not out the other from the comfort &amp; benefit of it. That which gives the ſoul <hi>union</hi> with Chriſt, doth give it <hi>communion</hi> with all the benefits of Chriſt. Chriſt and his benefits go toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Yet I could wiſh that every one who hath done this firſt <hi>act</hi> of faith, would work it up one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree higher, to <hi>apprehend</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply Chriſt in the promiſes of grace. Seeing according to the meaſure of your faith, and feeding upon Chriſt; ſuch is the meaſure of the benefit by Chriſt here. But however, be not diſcouraged, ſuch as are <hi>weak</hi> in faith will Chriſt receive.
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.1.</note> If hee have a care that others ſhall not reject them for their weakneſs, but bid them to receive them, much more will <hi>hee</hi> himſelf receive them; and whom he will receive ſhall receive him.</p>
            <p>If therefore thou art weak in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97618:34"/>
               <hi>applying</hi> faith, and thou cannot bring Chriſt over to thee, <hi>go</hi> thou <hi>over</hi> to Chriſt; if thou cannot <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> apprehend him, let him <hi>appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend</hi> thee,
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.12.</note> caſt thy ſelf into his arms;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dâ fide ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis nos ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto, quàm quod nos ipſum ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>henda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> Chem.</note> by this act ſet thy <hi>ſeal</hi> to Gods truth, and expect here in this ordinance that God ſhould put his <hi>Seal</hi> to thy heart by aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. So much for the firſt, what act of faith is here to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed. We come to the ſecond.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Upon what <hi>Object</hi> muſt the act of faith be terminated here? You muſt know there are <hi>many objects</hi> of faith in generall; as God himſelf in the unity of Eſſence, and trinity of Perſons, the <hi>Word</hi> of God, the <hi>Promiſes</hi> of God. But there is but one object of Juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faith, and that is Chriſt, <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 10.43 Gen. 3.15.</note> the Mediatour. <hi>To him give all the Prophets witneſs, that who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver believes in him, ſhall receive re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of ſins.</hi> This is the <hi>object</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:97618:34"/>upon which the <hi>faith</hi> of <hi>Adam</hi> was terminated,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> the ſeed of the woman, and thereby was juſtified, and had his <hi>recovery</hi> after the fall. This is that <hi>object</hi> upon which the <hi>faith</hi> of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who was the Father of the faithfull, was ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated, who ſaw his day and rejoyced; it was not the believing of the <hi>Promiſe</hi> of ſeed, but in the <hi>promiſed</hi> ſeed. To him alſo did the eyes of the <hi>faithfull</hi> look un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the law, through the ſhadows and ſacrifices, and were juſtified by Chriſt to <hi>be,</hi> as we are now by Chriſt <hi>exhibited.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And upon him muſt our faith be terminated, not only in the firſt act of faith for juſtification, but alſo in the exerciſe of it in this ordinance for the further aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of juſtification, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of ſanctification.</p>
            <p>And let it not ſeem <hi>ſtrange</hi> to you, wee are not ſo much to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97618:35"/>deale with a <hi>promiſe</hi> here as with the <hi>thing promiſed,</hi> nor to feed on a <hi>promiſe</hi> as upon <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf by faith, to eat his fleſh and drinke his blood,
<note place="margin">Matth. 26.26. <hi>Corpus Chriſtieſt pabulum fidei.</hi> Joh. 6.15.</note> 
               <hi>This is my body,</hi> &amp;c. Chriſt is the <hi>meat</hi> here for the hand of faith to receive, the mouth of faith to eate, as hee faith, <hi>My fleſh is meat indeed, and my blood is drink indeed.</hi> You may make uſe of the <hi>promiſes</hi> here, the Sacrament is the <hi>ſeale</hi> to every promiſe in the covenant. But the <hi>matter</hi> of the Sacrament indeed, and that whereon wee are chiefly to feed, is <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe. <hi>Chriſt</hi> as he is laid out unto us in his <hi>death</hi> and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, whereon feeding, wee get ſpirituall <hi>nouriſhment</hi> for grace, and <hi>death</hi> of ſinne. The blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> like the <hi>waters</hi> appointed for the triall of jealouſie, hath a double property, to <hi>kill</hi> and to make <hi>fruitfull;</hi> to kill our <hi>ſinnes,</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:97618:35"/>and make our <hi>graces</hi> grow; to <hi>rot</hi> our ſins, and <hi>ripen</hi> our grace.</p>
            <p>Well then, remember that the great diſh thou feedſt on at this Feaſt, be <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chriſto ſublato ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil reſtat in ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, praeter inaneſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaculum.</hi> Dav. in col.</note> Thou canſt not <hi>feed</hi> upon a promiſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till thou firſt <hi>feed</hi> upon <hi>Chriſt;</hi> he doth not onely give us <hi>title</hi> and intereſt in them, but <hi>appetite</hi> to them. If thou feed on him, thy <hi>ſtomach</hi> will be quicker to feed on them; nay, if thou feed on him,
<note place="margin">Christus eſt ſubſtantia ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum; &amp; ejus opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio eſt ipſa vita ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentorum.</note> thou feedeſt on all the promiſes, and haſt an intereſt in all the good of them, the ſweet of all the promiſes is taſted in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> All the promiſes are folded up in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and thou canſt not feed on him, but thou feedeſt on all, and haſt the <hi>bleſsing</hi> of every one in particular. The promiſes of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, ſanctification, ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of corruptions, increaſe of grace, upholding in grace, intereſt in glory, they are all of them fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97618:36"/>up in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> hee is all.</p>
            <p>The <hi>promiſe</hi> doth not, but <hi>Chriſt doth juſtifie,</hi> Chriſt doth ſanctifie; you get nothing from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe <hi>ſeparate</hi> from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but all the good of the promiſe comes in by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and therefore here terminate your faith. And ſo much for the ſecond, upon what object wee muſt terminate our Faith. We come to the third.</p>
            <p>For what benefit muſt Faith here be exerciſed?
<note place="margin">Partic. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, faith muſt not bee here acted for your <hi>juſtification;</hi> it is required you ſhould be juſtified perſons, have your ſins forgiven before you come hither. He that comes hither under the guilt of ſin, goes away with more guilt, and his former guilt is doubled and confirmed on him. So that for this benefit faith is not to bee acted, as wee ſhall ſhew here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:97618:36"/>
            <p>Secondly, faith muſt not be here acted for <hi>Regeneration;</hi> It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired a man ſhould be borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, bee in the ſtate of grace, ſanctified, before hee come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Here is the <hi>multiplying</hi> of grace, but no <hi>begetting</hi> of grace. As in the miracle of <hi>loaves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 14.19.</note> there was no new bread created, but a multiplying of the bread they had: So here is no giving of grace where there is none, but a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of grace where it is: where grace is, there it is <hi>increaſed,</hi> but it is not here begotten. A man may come to the Word though he be graceleſſe,
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.14.</note> becauſe the Word is an Ordinance ſet up for the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of men, and begetting ſouls to <hi>Chriſt:</hi> but none are to come to the Sacrament, but ſuch as are begotten anew; the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not the <hi>Font,</hi> it is not the place where men are born, but the table where men are nouriſhed; it
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97618:37"/>is not the <hi>ſeed</hi> of the new birth, but the <hi>meat</hi> of the new born, we muſt be <hi>born</hi> before we eat, <hi>bred</hi> before fed, <hi>begotten</hi> before nouriſhed. If we come <hi>graceleſs</hi> hither, we ſhall go <hi>graceleſs</hi> away, and worſe then we came. In particular then:</p>
            <p>Faith muſt here be exerciſed for the further <hi>aſſurance of our juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> God hath caſt down the ſoule by the miniſtery of the Word, hee hath diſcovered and revealed the promiſe, brought the ſoule over to the promiſe, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which it reſts, and is juſtified, and hither we come to be further aſſured of it. This was one end why the Sacrament was ſet up. We know the ſtrongeſt are but weake in faith:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fides non toll it, ſed vincit om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitationem.</hi> Dav.</note> there is no ſuch aſſurance in the world as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell all doubts &amp; fears, though to overcome them; but though they may be <hi>ſuſpended</hi> in their actings for a time, and well ſubdued and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97618:37"/>conquered, yet they are not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether expelled; if they were, then were there no need of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for this <hi>end,</hi> to confirme and ſtrengthen faith,
<note place="margin">Fides po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt habere aliquem modum du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitationis ſalvâ fide.</note> and ſo one of the ends wherfore God ſet up this <hi>Ordinance,</hi> were in vaine to that man. But I ſay there is no man ſo ſure, but may be ſurer: there are degrees of <hi>aſſurance</hi> as well as faith, and ſo may we grow up in aſſurance as well as faith. And now for the further aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of our juſtification, God to the covenant of grace and mercie, wherein he promiſed the free pardon of ſin, hath annexed the <hi>Seale</hi> of the covenant, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may be more aſſured.</p>
            <p>Indeed here is no need of this in reſpect of <hi>God,</hi> our juſtification is ſure with him, his <hi>intention</hi> is as good as his promiſe, his <hi>promiſe</hi> as his oath, his <hi>oath</hi> as his ſeale. But it was God's <hi>goodneſſe</hi> to us,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97618:38"/>pitying the weakneſſe of our faith; he ſtooped below himſelf, and was not only content to give us his promiſe, but to confirm it with his oath, the great ſeale of Heaven, and to all this to afford his Sacraments, to ſeale up all unto us,
<note place="margin">Heb. 18.19.</note> that we might have <hi>ſtrong aſsurance</hi> and conſolation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18. It was to this end, to aſſure us, who have ſuch unbeleeving hearts, that God gave word upon word, promiſe upon promiſe, oath to oath, ſeale to ſeale, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping mountain upon mountain, and all to confirm our ſtaggering hearts. That we might be <hi>ſtrong</hi> in him, when <hi>weak</hi> in our ſelves; <hi>faithfull</hi> in him, when <hi>fearfull</hi> in our ſelves; <hi>ſtedfaſt</hi> in him, when we <hi>ſtagger</hi> in our ſelves.</p>
            <p>And how ſhould we exerciſe <hi>faith</hi> here, and go doubting away? How ſhall we go away <hi>trembling</hi> after all this confirmation? An <hi>oath</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:97618:38"/>among men is the end of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, the concluding of all difference and diſputes; and ſhall not God's oath prevail thus much with you? Why doe you ſuffer returne of feares and doubts, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch a ſeale? Woe be to us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vae nobis ſi nec juran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti Deo cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus.</hi> Aug.</note> if we will not beleeve God, no not upon his oath. Doeſt thou deſire better ſecurity? Thou ſhalt never have it, thou canſt not. If you would come up to God, and take his ſecurity, how could you doubt?</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond benefit for the compaſſing of which faith muſt be exerciſed, &amp;c. is the <hi>increaſe</hi> of our <hi>graces,</hi> or perfecting of our ſanctification. My brethren, we are weak in grace; you know how much infidelity, and how little faith; how much enmity, how little love; how much obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie, how little pliable confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to his will; what a deale of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97618:39"/>formality, how little power; what hardneſſe of heart, how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle brokenneſſe of ſpirit for ſin? &amp;c. And being weak in <hi>grace,</hi> there is a <hi>neceſsity</hi> that theſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhould bee nouriſhed. As there is neceſſitie of <hi>daily bread,</hi> for the nouriſhing and upholding of our bodies; ſo there is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of <hi>ſpirituall food</hi> for the nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing of grace in our ſoules. And as there is neceſſity of our nouriſhment, ſo is there neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty our nouriſhment ſhould come from Chriſt, he is the ſtaff of nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment.
<note place="margin">Eo modo quo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramur, nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimur.</note> As in <hi>naturall</hi> life the ſame way we are begotten, the ſame way we are nouriſhed: ſo in <hi>ſpirituall</hi> life, Chriſt hee is the <hi>Breeder,</hi> and ſo he is the <hi>Feeder</hi> of grace in us; he is the <hi>Begetter,</hi> and he is the <hi>Nouriſher.</hi> From Chriſt we have our <hi>graces,</hi> he is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain from whoſe fulneſſe wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive grace for grace in our <hi>rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration;</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:97618:39"/>and he is the nouriſhment of whoſe fulneſſe wee receive
<note n="*" place="margin">Gratiam gratiae ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam.</note> grace to grace in our <hi>ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Hence he is called the <hi>Bread</hi> of life, not onely becauſe he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets life in <hi>dead</hi> men, but becauſe he nouriſheth and maintaineth life in <hi>living</hi> men. He is <hi>panis ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualis,</hi> ſpirituall bread, in the word to beget life; and <hi>panis Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentalis,</hi> bread in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Sacramentall bread, to nouriſh and to maintain life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten; and hereafter he ſhall be <hi>panis aeternalis,</hi> our daily bread in heaven, to preſerve us in holineſs with happineſs to all eternity. And as there is a <hi>neceſsity</hi> of nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, and nouriſhment by Chriſt; ſo Chriſt for this end, that we might be nouriſhed, hath ſet up this ordinance of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, for the <hi>nouriſhment</hi> of the Saints in grace, for the <hi>ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening</hi> our faith, to which it hath
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:97618:40"/>a proper influence, being the <hi>ſeale</hi> of the covenant, and for the increaſing our ſorrow and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, unto which it hath the like influence, being the repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt wounded, broken, bleeding for ſinne; who looks on Chriſt bleeding, but his heart muſt bleed? &amp;c. And ſo of the reſt.</p>
            <p>Chriſt is a full fountaine, and unwilling to be a ſealed fountain to you;
<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gratia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivantur à Chriſto.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Efficatia operationis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Beneficio interceſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Merito paſsionis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Virtute applicatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> he is a treaſury of grace, and unwilling to be lockt up, and therefore hath been ſo gracious, as to ſet up an ordinance, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be a <hi>ſeale,</hi> but an <hi>inſtrument</hi> or conduit-pipe to convey grace to us from him, the Fountaine of all grace; which nouriſhment he doth convey unto us by vertue of our <hi>union</hi> and <hi>communion</hi> with him, and <hi>application</hi> of him to us in theſe <hi>ordinances;</hi> which though they be all <hi>ſecret</hi> wayes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97618:40"/>of nouriſhment, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ground, that the world can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee, yet there is <hi>reall</hi> nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment brought down to the ſoul, whereby the ſoul goes home in a better frame, faith more increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, affections more inlarged, our love more inflamed, our deſires more quickened, and yet more ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But I know you will ask of me, how faith is here to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, for the <hi>drawing down</hi> of life &amp; nouriſhment from Chriſt in this ordinance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For the anſwer of which in brief:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Faith looks upon Chriſt as the <hi>treaſury</hi> and common ſtock of grace, in whom dwels all fulneſs,
<note place="margin">Joh. 1.14.16. Joh. 3.34. Col. 1.19. Col. 2.3.9.</note> all our fulnes; faith looks on him as the <hi>univerſall principle</hi> of life and <hi>root</hi> of holineſs. God gave not him the Spirit in meaſure.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Faith caſts its eye on the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:97618:41"/>
               <hi>promiſe</hi> for the <hi>conveyance</hi> of grace from him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ille eſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalis gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae; &amp; ab illo nobis omnes ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vuli deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantur.</hi> Daven.</note> it ſees a promiſe for <hi>derivation</hi> of grace from him to us: Faith works, <hi>virtute promiſsi:</hi> by vertue of the promiſe; where there is no promiſe, there can be no faith, and therefore faith diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers, that there may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and participation with this fulneſs; there are ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes made that of his fulneſs we ſhall receive grace for grace, <hi>John</hi> 1.16. and Chriſt is made unto us Wiſdome, Righteouſnes, Sanctification, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. and he came that we might have life, and have it in abundance; <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.10.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ex ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praeſentant ex inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant, ex virtute Chriſti ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctificant,</hi> Aquin.</note> Faith looks upon this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance as an <hi>Inſtrument,</hi> a means which God hath ſet up for the conveying of life and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from Chriſt. Though God can do it without, yet in God's <hi>ordinary</hi> way, Ordinances are the means of the conveying of life from him to us.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:97618:41"/>4. Now then, faith being ſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by ſuch conſiderations as theſe, that there is a fulneſs in Chriſt, that there is a promiſe of this fulnes to be made over to us, and that the Sacrament is an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance wherby God as by an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument will convey of this ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt to a poor ſoul: faith goes over to Chriſt, and by <hi>vertue</hi> of the <hi>Promiſe,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying and feeding upon Chriſt, draws down further life and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment from him to the ſoul: As one ſaid of the <hi>tree</hi> of Chriſt's aſcenſion, though the fruit were high, and above our reach, yet if wee touch him by the hand of faith, and tongue of prayer, all will fall down upon us: So here, if we can but touch him with the hand of faith, though a palſie hand, though a weak and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling hand; if we can but goe to him with a praying heart, Chriſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:97618:42"/>can with-hold nothing from us.</p>
            <p>And after this manner doth faith form a Prayer to him: <q>Lord, thou knows I am weak in grace, thou ſeeſt my <hi>faith</hi> is feeble, my <hi>love</hi> cold, my <hi>deſires</hi> faint, my <hi>obedience</hi> ſmall; but thou haſt all <hi>fulneſs</hi> of grace; thou art the Fountain, and this Fountain is opened here; thou art the Treaſury, and this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury is here unlock'd. Thoſe <hi>graces</hi> I have, though weak, thou begatſt them, and wilt not thou now nouriſh them? From thee I had the <hi>being</hi> of grace, and from thee I muſt have the nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing. Thou haſt ſet up this <hi>Ordinance</hi> as a means to convey grace, and thou haſt promiſed to remember them that are in thy way,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 64.5.</note> therefore help,—&amp;c. Beſides, may faith ſay, Lord, thou haſt been pleaſed to <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant</hi> me into <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſhall I
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:97618:42"/>
                  <hi>die</hi> for <hi>want</hi> of nouriſhment? thou haſt made me a <hi>member</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſhall I <hi>decay</hi> and <hi>wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> for want of influence? Oh! never let it be ſaid, that a <hi>branch</hi> in <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall <hi>wither</hi> and <hi>decay</hi> for <hi>want</hi> of nouriſhment, when there is ſo much in the root; let it never be ſaid, that a <hi>member</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould <hi>wither</hi> and <hi>die</hi> for want of <hi>influence</hi> and life, ſeeing there is ſo much in the Head. Thou cameſt,
<note place="margin">Joh. 10.10</note> that I might have <hi>life;</hi> yea, &amp; have it in abundance; why Lord, my <hi>graces</hi> are weak, here are <hi>dying</hi> affections, <hi>dying</hi> diſpoſitions, <hi>dying</hi> graces, Oh! come down before I dye, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the things that are ready to dye in me.
<note place="margin">Rev. 3.2.</note> Thou haſt raiſed me from the <hi>death</hi> of ſin, let me not again <hi>drop</hi> into the ſame grave; thou haſt wrought <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> in mee, let them not <hi>decay</hi> for want of life, when ſuch
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97618:43"/>
                  <hi>abundance</hi> in thee.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus doth <hi>Chriſt, formed</hi> in the heart, cry out for <hi>Chriſt nouriſhing</hi> in the Sacrament. The work of grace is called a <hi>forming</hi> of Chriſt in the ſoul,
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.9.</note> and Chriſt doth but <hi>nouriſh</hi> and feed <hi>himſelf,</hi> his own graces here. <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> doth nouriſh <hi>Chriſt</hi> begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the heart by the <hi>Word.</hi> And the ſoul feeding upon <hi>Chriſt</hi> by faith, is further <hi>changed</hi> into his Image. In our <hi>corporall</hi> feeding, the meat is changed into the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the eater, but in our <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall</hi> feeding, the eater is changed into the nature of the meat eaten, the Believer into the nature of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. <hi>While beholding him as in a glaſs, we are alſo changed into his Image.</hi>— Thus doth faith <hi>feed</hi> upon Chriſt, and draw down nouriſhment for the ſtrength of every grace in us, &amp;c. And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>meaſure</hi> of faith's feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97618:43"/>ſuch is the <hi>proportion</hi> and <hi>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> of nouriſhment conveyed. As the <hi>ſtomach</hi> ſendeth down nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment to all parts, from the <hi>ſupply</hi> of food, which it hath fed on: Or, as the <hi>Liver</hi> having drawn down and made blood from the nouriſhment in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, diffuſeth and ſpreadeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and ſends to every part ſome: So <hi>Faith,</hi> having fed upon Chriſt, doth here ſend down nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment to all the <hi>graces:</hi> or, as in a <hi>Feaſt,</hi> you ſend portions to your poor brethren; ſo <hi>Faith</hi> having <hi>feaſted</hi> it ſelf on <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſends down portions to her ſiſter-graces. All our <hi>graces</hi> have a <hi>dependance</hi> on Faith, and <hi>Faith</hi> on <hi>Chriſt;</hi> our Graces depend on Faith as a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour</hi> to our Mediatour: as that grace which hath <hi>immediately</hi> to do with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> from whence it fetcheth ſupply and proviſion for all the reſt. That is the ſecond
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:97618:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>benefit faith is here to be acted for.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third benefit that Faith is here to be exerciſed on <hi>Chriſt for,</hi> is <hi>the further ſubduing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering of our corruptions.</hi> Faith hath a <hi>double work</hi> to do; It works in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and it works in <hi>Earth:</hi> As it works in <hi>Heaven</hi> for the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of a ſin, ſo it works in <hi>earth</hi> for the mortification of ſin; and here in this <hi>Ordinance</hi> is faith acted on <hi>Chriſt</hi> for the further <hi>kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> of ſin. Faith hath a ſpecial <hi>art</hi> in going over to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> &amp; fetching from him ſuch help as is ſutable to the neceſſities of the ſoul. If we be <hi>weak</hi> in Graces, Faith can go over to <hi>Chriſt</hi> for the ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them. If <hi>corruptions</hi> be ſtrong, Faith can go over to <hi>Chriſt</hi> for the ſubduing, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering of them. And by making uſe of the merit, power, promiſe, Spirit of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> gets ſtrength
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:97618:44"/>from him for the ſubduing of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly luſts, untamed corruptions. <q>Why, will Faith ſay, Lord, thou haſt <hi>promiſed</hi> to ſubdue my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and thou art <hi>able</hi> to ſubdue all to thy ſelf, Oh! there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſet thy <hi>power</hi> againſt the power of my luſts. Theſe ſons of <hi>Zerviah</hi> are too ſtrong for me, but not for thee: I am <hi>bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened</hi> with a dead heart, a hard heart, unbelieving heart, &amp;c. But never was there <hi>heart</hi> ſo hard, but thou canſt break it; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heart ſo <hi>dead,</hi> but thou canſt <hi>quicken</hi> it. There is <hi>life</hi> enough in thee for all the ſons and daughters of <hi>death</hi> in the world, oh! that therfore thou would'ſt quicken me, that thou would'ſt break me</q>— Thus doth Faith make uſe of Chriſt here for the <hi>ſubduing</hi> of corruptions.</p>
            <p>And let me tell you, there is a ſpeciall art, dexterity and skill
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:97618:45"/>which faith hath, wherby it forms ſuch <hi>conceptions</hi> of Chriſt, as are ever <hi>ſutable</hi> to the preſent neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the ſoul, whereby it gets more ſpeedy relief.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If there be a <hi>return of guilt</hi> upon the ſoul, and burthen upon the conſcience. Faith looks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſt in <hi>blood,</hi> Chriſt a Prieſt, a Sacrifice for ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the ſoul labour under <hi>ignorance,</hi> Faith looks upon him as the great <hi>Prophet</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> and ſaith, Lord, thou haſt taken upon thee to be the great <hi>Prophet</hi> of the Church,
<note place="margin">Joh. 6.45. Iſa. 14.13. Jer. 31.34.</note> thou haſt promiſed wee ſhall be all taught of God. Oh! therefore teach me, inſtruct me, &amp;c. It is not ſo ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to look upon Chriſt as a Prieſt, when we deſire he ſhould do the work of a Prophet.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If we be weak in grace, faith looks upon him as the univerſall fountain and principle of grace,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:97618:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>one who hath all fulneſs in him, able to fill a world of hearts with grace, though they were never ſo barren or empty; And ſo goes over to him for ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">Mal. 3.2.</note> If we labour under the pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of ſin, faith looks upon Chriſt as a refiner, a purifier, a purger of his people from ſin. As one who came not only to be a Redeemer, but a refiner; not only a Saviour,
<note place="margin">Eph. 5.26. Tit. 2.14.</note> but a ſanctifier of his people, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14.</p>
            <p n="5">5, And ſo, if corruptions be ſtrong, faith looks upon him as a King, who is able to ſubdue and conquer unruly affections, and to bring every thing into ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to himſelf.</p>
            <p>God hath not only furniſhed Chriſt with fulneſs of ſupply to anſwer every need of the ſoul, but God hath given to Chriſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of titles, that wee might
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:97618:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>conceive of him not only as a ful, but as a ſutable good to every ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the ſoul. And God, having thus diverſly repreſented <hi>Chriſt</hi> to our underſtandings, as a Prophet, a Prieſt, a King, a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finer, &amp;c. Faith doth form ſuch conceptions of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as are moſt ſutable to the preſent neceſſity of the ſoul.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A fourth benefit for which Faith may be exerciſed in this Ordinance, is for deliverance out of temptations. Thou haſt been long aſſaulted by Satan;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vnus filius ſine pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, nullus ſine tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione.</hi> 1 Cor. 10.13. 2 Cor. 12.9. Heb. 2.18. Rom. 16.20.</note> thou haſt felt the blows and buffets of Satan many yeers; God hath not only promiſed to ſupport thee and ſuccour thee in this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but God hath promiſed to deliver thee out of this condition <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20. <hi>The God of peace ſhall tread down Satan under your feet ſhortly.</hi> Why now exerciſe faith to ſue out theſe promiſes God hath
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:97618:46"/>made; go over to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for ſtrength and ſupport in the condition, but for victory and deliverance out of it. Theſe dayes, they are not only God's ſealing, but God's performing dayes: God doth not only here put his ſeal to every Promiſe folded up in the covenant, but hee is ready here to make per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the things he hath promiſed. And therefore go ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a catalogue of promiſes, which ſuits with thy condition, ſpread them before God, and here come ſue them out in this Ordinance.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the firſt grace which is to bee exerciſed in this ordinance, namely <hi>Faith.</hi> And I have ſhewed you, 1. what Act, 2. upon what Object, 3. for what benefits faith is here to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed. I have named foure, but here is not all; the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97618:47"/>is the Seale of the whole covenant, and what ever particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar benefits are folded up in the great draught and covenant of God, here you may exerciſe faith for the compaſſing and obtaining of them. Where ever there is a promiſe in the Word, there is work for faith to ſue it out in this ordinance, which is the ſeale to all, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By the way then, this may diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to us, where the fault is, when we return home, our faith never the more ſtrengthened, our hearts never the more warm'd, our graces never the more nouriſhed, our corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s never the more weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. It is a ſhrewd ſign faith did not play its part in the mount. It is great ſuſpition that your faith did <hi>ſuccumbere in conatu,</hi> did faile and ſink in the encounter. Faith was intruſted in this imploiment to goe over to Chriſt for theſe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:97618:47"/>benefits, and thy faith did faile in the undertaking; therefore God ſuſpends the beſtowing of theſe benefits, becauſe thou ſuſpendeſt thy faith.</p>
            <p>A man may halt after his ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with God, and yet over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, as <hi>Jacob</hi> did; but when a man's ſpirit doth halt in ſtriving with God, when we doe not ſtrive fully with God, there is little hope of prevailing. Well then, if thou ſee not the fruit and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit thou expected to come into thy ſoule in the uſe of this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, charge thy faith with it, and bewaile the weakneſſe of it: and for the future put it to its burden, let it have its full and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect worke, and thou wilt then find the comfort and fruit of it. Never did faith touch Chriſt in any Ordinance, but vertue came from him. But ſo much for the firſt Grace—</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:97618:48"/>2.
<note place="margin">2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Grace to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed.</note> A ſecond grace which is here to be exerciſed in the uſe of this Ordinance, and requiſite to the ſanctification of God in it, is <hi>Repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sacraments they are the crucifixes of Chriſt, in which Chriſt is repreſented as cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied afreſh before our eyes: the bread broken doth preach unto us the breaking of Chriſt: The wine powred forth doth preach unto us the Blood of Chriſt poured forth for our ſinnes. And who is it that can with the eye of faith, look upon a broken Chriſt, but with a broken heart? a wounded Chriſt, but with a wounded ſpirit? a bleeding Chriſt but with a bleeding ſoule? God hath made in nature the ſame or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan for ſeeing and weeping: And in grace hee who ſees clearly, weeps throughly, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.5. <hi>The eye will affect the heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:97618:48"/>
            <p>The Paſſeover under the Law was to be eaten with bitter herbs: So Chriſt, the true Paſſover, is here to be eaten with bitterneſſe of ſoul: as it was propheſied; <hi>They ſhal look on him whom they have pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and ſhall lament, and mourne; firſt ſeeing, and then weeping, &amp;c.</hi> Zach. 12.10.</p>
            <p>There is a twofold mourning, 1. Hiſtoricall; 2. Spirituall. 1. Hiſtoricall mourning; there is a naturall tenderneſſe in men and women, whereby their hearts doe yearn and melt to heare the relation, or behold the ſight of ſome ſad ſtory. Such a one as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> confeſſeth he had when he read the ſad ſtory of <hi>Dido:</hi> and yet his heart was hard, he could not mourn for ſin. Or ſuch a one as they had, whom Chriſt blamed in the Goſpel, who lamented the cruell uſage of Chriſt out of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall compaſſion only; to whom
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:97618:49"/>he ſaith, <hi>O daughters of Jeruſalem, weep not for me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Homini non eſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarium ut Chriſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ipſius paſſione deploret, ſed magis ut ſeipſum in Chriſto.</note> Of this the Father ſpeaks, <hi>It is not neceſſary you lament his paſsion, ſo much as your ſinnes, which have cauſed his paſsion.</hi> There is a kind of naturall tenderneſs in men and women, wihch yet is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten joyned with hardneſſe of heart for ſinne. As an Hiſtorical faith, with ſpirituall unbelief, and an Hiſtoricall love, with ſpiritual enmity; ſo a natural tenderneſſe, with ſpirituall hardneſſe of heart for ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is a ſpirituall mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which ariſeth from ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all grounds and cauſes, and tends to ſpirituall ends. A ſorrow which is cauſed by faith, looking upon heart-melting promiſes, or taking up heart-breaking conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, or beholding a heart-ſoftning object, by which Faith doth draw waters out of the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of the ſoul for ſin, as you
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:97618:49"/>have it, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.6. they drew water (as out of a well) and pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it forth before the Lord. And this is that ſorrow which is here to be exerciſed, which will melt and mellow the heart, and cauſe it to be more fruitfull in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. Never doth the garden of graces better grow, then after ſuch a ſhowre of repentant tears. And therefore doth God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve theſe ſprings in the ſoul, to water the ſeeds of grace, and make us more fruitfull, which it ſurely doth when they are Sun-ſhine-ſhowres, ſuch ſhowres wherein the Sun appeares, Chriſt is not hid from the eye of faith.</p>
            <p>And, my brethren, here are many things in this ordinance, which if but looked upon with the eye of faith, will open all the ſprings of ſorrow in the ſoule, and call forth all the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in him. <hi>Bellarnine</hi> he layes
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:97618:50"/>down twelve conſiderations to provoke ſorrow, as the miſeries of mankind by nature, the ſad condition of the ſouls in Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and ſuch like ſtuffe. But we need not be beholding to him for ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiderations as theſe, to oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion mourning. Here is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in the Sacrament pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the eye of faith, to open all the Springs thou haſt, and if thou had a fountaine of teares, to ſpend them all for ſinne. We will name ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars here which draw out mournings.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Here is a diſcovery of the love and ſweetneſſe of God, in giving his Son to die for us.
<note place="margin">Joh. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>So God loved the world, &amp;c.</hi> enough to cauſe us to mourne that ever wee offended. <q>Oh that God ſhould bee more tender to us then to his owne Sonne, not ſpare his Sonne that he might
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:97618:50"/>ſpare us, give him to die, that we might live, poure the curſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, that the bleſſing might bee poured on us!</q>
               <note place="margin">Quis tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peret à la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymis?</note> O how ſhould this affect us! Who can think of this, and with-hold from teares?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Here is preſented to us the ſufferings and breakings of Chriſt, enough to break our har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt hearts. 1. The ſufferings of Chriſt, <hi>in ſe,</hi> in themſelves, as thoſe upon his body; what brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings? what woundings? what ſcourgings? what crownings, piercings, did he endure in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? and thoſe in his ſoule: What conflicts and ſtruglings did he undergoe with the wrath of God, the terrors of death, the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of darknes? Oh what weight, what burden, what wrath did hee undergoe, when his ſoule was hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie unto death? beſet with ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, as the word ſignifies, when
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:97618:51"/>he drank that bitter cup,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Vndequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que triſtis, valde tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis,</hi> Paſſor. <hi>Supra mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum dolens</hi> Scap. <hi>Obſitus terrori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> Ariſt.</note> that cup mingled with curſes, which if Man or Angell had but ſipt of, it would have ſunk them into hell; Nay, it made him, who was God as well as man, ſanctified by the Spirit, ſupported with the Deity, comforted by Angels, ſweat ſuch a ſweat as never man ſweat; drops, clods of blood,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>tanquam grumi ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinis.</hi>
               </note> as the word im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider them <hi>in Causâ,</hi> as the meriting cauſe of all our good, the procurers of all our peace, ſalvation, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>He was wounded, that we might be healed; ſcourged, that we might be ſolaced; drunk the cup of wrath, a bitter cup, to procure all our ſweet draughts: He was ſlain, ſaith <hi>Daniel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Dan. 9.26.</note> but not for himſelf; he was wounded for our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, broken for our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; the chaſtiſement of our peace was upon him, and by his
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:97618:51"/>ſtripes are we healed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.5, 8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider them as <hi>effectus pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati,</hi> as the effects of our ſin, as thoſe things our ſins brought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him,
<note place="margin">Solvere ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licidium.</note> and needs muſt this melt and thaw our Icie &amp; ſtony hearts. Oh, will the ſoul ſay! it hath been I who have been the traytor, the murtherer, my ſins which have been bloody inſtruments to ſlay the Lord of glory. I have ſinn'd,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.</note> thou ſuffer'd; 'twas I that did eat the ſowre grapes, yet thy teeth were ſet on edge; I have been thy death, yet thy death hath given mee life; I have wounded thee, yet thou haſt healed me; yea, and even out of that wound my ſins made, thou ſent a plaiſter to heal mee. This conſideration muſt needs fill the heart with ſorrow, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. <hi>They ſhall look upon him whom they have pierced,</hi> and how ſhall this ſight affect them? why, it follows, <hi>they ſhall mourn,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:97618:52"/>and be in bitterneſs of ſoul, as one in bitterneſs for their firſt-born.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They ſay, if one man kill ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and you bring the murtherer into the place, where the ſlain perſon lies, the dead will bleed afreſh: Wee are the murtherers of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and we come here to an Ordinance where <hi>Chriſt</hi> is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in his blood, as broken and wounded for our ſins. O! that our hearts might bleed! as he bleeds afreſh to us; ſo that wee might bleed a freſh to him. A Prince wil weep himſelf when the Page is whipped for him: but how ſhould the Page mourn when the Prince is ſcourged for him? My bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, there is infinite more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion between <hi>Chriſt</hi> and us, then between the Prince and the Page, the Lord and the ſlave. And how can we then look upon him as wounded, ſcourged, pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, for us, &amp; not be affected with,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:97618:52"/>afflicted for our <hi>ſin,</hi> the cauſe of it. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith,
<note n="*" place="margin">Sivis ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcere, ſicut ſe fregit, ita te fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge.</note> If thou would be conformable to <hi>Chriſt</hi> (in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament) as thou beholdeſt a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken &amp; a bleeding <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo labour to behold him w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> a broken bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heart. Look on him in this <hi>Ordinance,</hi> as <hi>Mary</hi> looked upon him on the Croſs, when <hi>Simeon's</hi> Propheſie was fulfilled, that a ſword ſhould paſs through her ſoul; <hi>Luke</hi> 2.35. for then indeed did a ſword paſs through her ſoul, when ſhe ſaw him pierced on the croſs: ſo when you ſee him pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and broken in the Sacrament, which is the lively repreſentation of <hi>Chriſt</hi> broken, Oh, that then it might be as a ſpear to our hearts! as a ſword to our ſpirits, that we by our ſins have wounded and pierced him!</p>
            <p>This is the ſecond grace to be exerciſed in this Ordinance. And beſide theſe two, there are
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:97618:53"/>many more to be exerciſed here, <hi>viz.</hi> Our love to God, our hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring and thirſting after <hi>Chriſt.</hi> There is that in <hi>Chriſt</hi> repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the eye of faith in this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, that calls out for all the affections, diſpoſitions, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires in you; You cannot ſee <hi>Chriſt</hi> here, but it will make eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grace within you ſtir, every diſpoſition within you to move, every wheel go. Who can ſee him but love him, who is ſo exceeding lovely? Who can ſee him but prize him, who is ſo exceeding precious? Who can ſee him but deſire him, who is ſo exceeding deſireable? Who can ſee him but delight in him, who is the joy and delight of the ſoul? You cannot poſſibly ſee him here, but all the powers of the ſoul will be up. 1. Your judgements to prize him, your wills to chooſe him, and make a new match with
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:97618:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>him; your affections to love him, embrace him, delight in him. And the clearer your ſight is here of <hi>Chriſt</hi> by faith, the more will your hearts be ſtirred, your ſpirits mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Men that ſit here as logs &amp; lumps of clay never ſtirred, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver taken up, they ſee not <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they ſee no higher then the table, the Bread and Wine, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dead and ſenſleſs. Oh! but if if one creviſe of your hearts were opened, to let in but one beam, one glimpſe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> it would ſet you all on a burning heavenly fire, this would warm you indeed. But beſides theſe graces to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, there is required ſome demeanours in the ſoul in this Ordinance, if we would ſanctifie God in it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. An humble and holy reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, which is the fruit of that dread and fear of God which is in the heart. There is abundance
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:97618:54"/>of lightneſs, looſeneſs and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the ſpirits of men by nature. And the Majeſty and dread of that great God, with whom wee have to do in this Ordinance, muſt conſolidate, and make our ſpirits weighty in theſe great Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances. The Sacrament is called an <hi>Euchariſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>grata be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiorum recordatio.</hi>
               </note> it is a gratulatory ſervice, and God is fearfull in praiſes, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.11. which hath ſpeciall reſpect to the affection wherewith you are to praiſe him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is required a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge &amp; diſmiſſion of all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoughts and buſineſſes. When <hi>Abraham</hi> went up to the Mount to ſacrifice, he left his ſervants in the valley. Thou art now to go up to the mount, where God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears. Oh! leave all your ſervile affections, your worldly thoughts in the valley. And if any enter, do as <hi>Abraham</hi> did by the Birds that would have eaten up his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:97618:54"/>chaſe them away; do by them as you do by ſtraggling beggars, give them their paſs, and ſend them away.</p>
            <p>In the Temple, though there was ſo much fleſh for ſacrifice, yet there was not one Flie appeared ſtirring; oh that it might be ſo with us this day! that not one thought might ariſe upon our hearts, unſutable to the place and work in hand. It is a thing unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting theſe great imployments, to have our hearts and thoughts taken up with other buſineſſes; what have you to do here with your ſhops, your bags, your cheſts? What have you here to do with things of this world?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit ſi me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditationes tuae in lege Dei ſint? &amp; ipſae in ſe ipſis ſine lege ſint.</hi> Bern. <hi>in Cant.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Oh make not this <hi>place</hi> an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, a <hi>Shop</hi> for merchandize, men are not able to do <hi>buſineſs</hi> in a crowd, nor you ſo great a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as this in a <hi>crowd</hi> of thoughts. But this is the miſery, you are
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:97618:55"/>
               <hi>ſervants</hi> and <hi>ſlaves</hi> to the <hi>world</hi> at other times, and therefore the <hi>world</hi> will <hi>maſter</hi> you now. If you paſs over your <hi>hearts</hi> to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the world at other times, the world will make you <hi>ſerve</hi> it now. Becauſe you have not <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall</hi> hearts in your <hi>temporall</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, therefore have you <hi>carnall</hi> hearts in your <hi>ſpirituall</hi> employments. The leſſe of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> in the <hi>week,</hi> the more you ſhall find of the <hi>week</hi> in the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</hi> The leſſe <hi>ſpirituall</hi> you are in affairs of <hi>earth,</hi> the more <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> you will bee in the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments of <hi>Heaven.</hi> This is certain, if the world once take your heart, it will take your head alſo. I ſay, if ever the world <hi>lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> your hearts, it will alſo <hi>poyſon</hi> your heads; it is a leaven diffuſeth it ſelf through the whole man. And therefore as Chriſt ſaid of the leaven of the Phariſees,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:97618:55"/>
               <hi>Take heed of the leaven of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, h. e.</hi> hypocriſie: (for if once the heart be <hi>leaven'd</hi> with that, it will ſoure the head: if the <hi>Principles</hi> are unſound, then are the <hi>purpoſes</hi> alſo, and performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces too, &amp;c.) So I ſay here, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of the leaven of worldly-mindedneſſe, if ever you would ſanctifie God in this ordinance. Beware of that, this will ſoure the ſoule, and make all you doe to be carnall and fleſhly. I tell you, if you be <hi>ſervants</hi> to the world at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times, the world will <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand</hi> and <hi>maſter</hi> you now. Thus much ſhall ſerve for the ſecond gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Head, <hi>What is required in the time for the ſanctification of this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance.</hi> We come to the third.</p>
            <p>To the ſanctifying God in an Ordinance, is required ſomthing after. And</p>
            <p>That now which is required af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, is, That you labour to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:97618:56"/>ſee the fruit of this ordinance to run downe through your lives. Thou exerciſedſt faith, labour to ſee thy heart more eſtabliſhed in <hi>aſſurance of pardon.</hi> See thy <hi>graces</hi> more ſtrengthened, thy <hi>corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> more weakned. I will name onely two things which are to follow the performance of this ordinance, if ever you would ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie God in it:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Thankfulneſſe,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Obedience.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gratiae nullu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius ſignum quam gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae.</hi> Aug.</note> Thankfulneſſe: Returne home now, as thy heart, full of the <hi>benefits</hi> of the <hi>Lord;</hi> ſo thy heart full of <hi>praiſes</hi> to the Lord. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels employments are moſt ſute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Angels food: thou haſt had Angels food, and let thy heart returne <hi>Angels</hi> retributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, praiſe and thankſgiving. If God doe but <hi>feed</hi> your bodies, there is none, I hope, ſuch <hi>beaſts,</hi> as will not return the retribution
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:97618:56"/>of praiſes: And will you be ſlow and backward to it when he hath fed your ſouls? Shall we bleſſe God for a <hi>Crumb,</hi> and not for a <hi>Chriſt?</hi> Other mercies are but crumbs in compariſon of this rich mercy, and ſhall our hearts ſavour them ſo much, &amp; not reliſh theſe?
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Divitiae dantur,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Bonis, ne puten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur mala.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Malis, ne putentur bona.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Multis, ne puten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur magnae.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> Other mercies he gives to his enemies, wicked men may run away w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> the greateſt <hi>portion</hi> of belly-bleſſings; but theſe hee only beſtowes on his friends: and ſhall we be unthankful for them? How ever <hi>carnall</hi> men are moſt taken with carnal things; yet ſure I am, thoſe who are <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> as they are moſt <hi>apprehenſive</hi> of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall wants; ſo the greateſt <hi>lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> out of their ſpirits in thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, is for ſpirituall enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. What's corne and wine, &amp;c. to this? This is a mercie in which all other mercies are fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded up, the <hi>ſummum genus</hi> of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:97618:57"/>the top-mercy.
<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quid tibi ſufficit, ſi Chriſtus non ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit? Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum habes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mnia ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Omne bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aut ipſe eſt, aut ab ipſo.</hi> Aug. <hi>de doct. Chri.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> God doth <hi>emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently</hi> contain al other comforts, and therefore in the want of all he can cheere the heart, <hi>Hah.</hi> 3.7. So Chriſt doth eminently contain all other mercies, and in the want of all, Chriſt enjoyed, is exceeding great reward. Nay, all mercies are not onely folded up in him, and intail'd to him, but he ſweetens and ſanctifies every mercie. Let us then return home as full of the bleſſing from on high, ſo full of praiſes to the moſt high. Thankfulneſſe is the great grace to bee exerciſed in, and thankfulneſſe is the great grace to be exerciſed after; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore while the preſent ſenſe of this mercie warmes your hearts, let the heat of it burſt forth into thankfulneſſe towards God; it is the moſt <hi>ſutable</hi> ſervice, and the moſt ſutable time to returne it. The beſt time to have <hi>thanfulneſs</hi>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:97618:57"/>in our hearts, is when we can look there, and finde the mercy for w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> we praiſe him alſo. The beſt time for praiſes and thankfulneſs in our mouths, is when wee have the bleſſing in our <hi>hands.</hi> Well then, all you who are right partakers of this Ordinance, ſummon up your hearts to return thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to God. And let your thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs carry ſome <hi>proportion</hi> with the <hi>mercy.</hi> The mercy is great, do but meaſure it in all the dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of it, how high? how deep? how broad a mercy? pardoning, purging mercy, and how long? even to all eternity; And as the mercy is great, ſo ſhould be the praiſes. (The more a man's <hi>appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions</hi> are enwidened to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of the vaſtneſs and greatneſs of the mercy, the more will the affections be inlarged to praiſe him for it. There was never man that did know the <hi>preciouſneſs</hi> of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:97618:58"/>Chriſt, and his own need of him, in reſpect of pardon, purging, and his own unworthineſs to partake of ſo glorious a mercy, but had his heart mightily inlarged to praiſe God for it. This is that then which God expects at your hands, after he hath <hi>filled</hi> you with the <hi>bleſsing</hi> of Heaven, that you ſhould return <hi>praiſes</hi> to Heaven. Though hee doth not reap where he doth not ſow, as that idle ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant charged him; yet where God <hi>ſowes</hi> bleſſings, hee expects to <hi>reap</hi> praiſes. Where there is a <hi>flood</hi> of mercy, hee looks for a <hi>ſtream</hi> of thankfulneſs. Oh! then let us proportion our returns to our receits, let us ſet up monuments of praiſe in our hearts and lives for this great mercy; Say with <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſs the Lord, ô my ſoul,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing required after this Ordinance, is obedience and fruitfulnes. That now for the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:97618:58"/>time to come, you ſhould apply your hearts to walk more worthy of God unto all manner of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: 1. That we ſhould have our hearts further ſet againſt ſin: 2. That we ſhould have our hearts further ſtrengthned to ſervice.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Get your hearts now fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſet againſt ſin. Oh! let your ſouls ſay, <q>Hath God been ſo gracious, as to <hi>renew</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm my <hi>pardon,</hi> and ſhall I again <hi>diſhonour</hi> him? Hath hee <hi>wiped</hi> off my former <hi>ſcores,</hi> and ſhall I run on <hi>afreſh</hi> to offend him? Hath hee taken off my former <hi>burthen,</hi> and caſt it on the back of his dear Son, and ſhall I again lay <hi>more</hi> load upon him? Hath he ſpoken <hi>peace</hi> to me in his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and ſhall I again <hi>return</hi> to folly? No, far be it from me. <hi>I have waſhed my feet, how ſhall I again defile them? I have put off my coat, how ſhal I again put it on?</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:97618:59"/>ſaith the Chriſtian ſoul.</q> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane men, they do by their <hi>ſins,</hi> as the <hi>Serpent</hi> with his <hi>poyſon,</hi> lay it aſide when they go to <hi>drink,</hi> but afterward take it up: Or, as men do with a <hi>garment,</hi> put it off at night, but put it on in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And this is fearfull, <hi>to return with the dog to the vomit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.22</note> But God's people caſt them away,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.22.</note> as a <hi>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruous</hi> rag, never more to have to do with them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Get your hearts further ſtrengthened to ſervice. Here is in this Ordinance a <hi>mutuall</hi> ſealing of Covenants between God and you. As God <hi>ſeals</hi> to thee, ſo thou <hi>ſeals</hi> again to God. God ſeals to the firſt part of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> pardon, mercy, grace; and thou ſeals to the ſecond part of it, ſervice, ſubjection, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: God <hi>gives Chriſt</hi> to thee here in this Ordinance, and thou <hi>gives</hi> thy <hi>ſelf</hi> back again to Chriſt. As
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:97618:59"/>there is matter of <hi>bountie</hi> from God to thee, ſo there is matter of <hi>duty</hi> from thee to God; God here in <hi>bounty</hi> beſtowes Chriſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every humble, broken hearted and believing receiver: They take him, and <hi>re-give</hi> themſelves back again to him for ſubjection and obedience. There was never any ſoul, to whom God ſaid in this Ordinance, <hi>I am thine,</hi> whoſe hearts did not eccho again the ſame to God, Lord, <hi>I am thine.</hi> This <hi>head</hi> is thine to contrive thy glory, this <hi>hand</hi> is thine to work for thee, this <hi>hart</hi> is thine to love thee, He that ſayes, <hi>my beloved is mine,</hi> ſayes again, <hi>and I am his;</hi> Cant. 2.16.
<note place="margin">Cant. 2.16</note> Let us then labour to ſee our hearts further ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened to ſervice; let this inable thee to walk:</p>
            <p n="1">1. More ſtrongly; The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are our <hi>ſpirituall</hi> baitings and refreſhments which God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:97618:60"/>us to ſtrengthen us in our <hi>journey</hi> to Heaven: They are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall meat &amp; drink to <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> us in the performance of al ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall obedience; ſuch meat as will not only <hi>inable</hi> a man to work, but to <hi>work</hi> more ſtrongly. And 'tis to be feared, that they who are never the ſtronger for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, feed not upon the <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> but upon the <hi>ſhadow,</hi> they feed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the elements, but never taſt of Chriſt the ſtaff of nouriſhment;
<note place="margin">Purum ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum non eſt ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum.</note> and tis true here, the meer <hi>element</hi> is no <hi>nouriſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. More willingly and cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; <hi>Then ſhall wee be able to run the wayes of God's Commandements,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.</note> when God once here inlarges our hearts. It is ſaid of <hi>Jacob,</hi> that when he had been <hi>refreſhed</hi> with the preſence of God, he plucked up his feet, and went on cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. So here, when the ſoul hath been refreſhed with the <hi>preſence</hi>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:97618:60"/>of Chriſt, he will be able to walk more cheerfully in the wayes of God. The food we feed upon is Angels' food, and will inable us to <hi>Angels'</hi> imployments, <hi>h. e.</hi> to do our work with an <hi>Angels</hi> ſpirit, with all alacrity, cheerfulneſs, joy and delight; though not in the ſame <hi>equality,</hi> yet in the ſame <hi>quality,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Siquid bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni triſtè feceris, fit de te magis quam à te.</hi> Proſper.</note> though not in the ſame <hi>meaſure,</hi> yet in the ſame <hi>manner.</hi> And thus much for the ſecond generall, <hi>viz.</hi> How we muſt ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie God in an Ordinance.</p>
            <p>Wee will now come to the third generall, which is the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why, <hi>Who ever have to do with an Ordinance of God, muſt ſanctifie God in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Becauſe God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands it. God ſaith hee will be ſanctified; and God's <hi>will</hi> is our <hi>law.</hi> God doth not only <hi>command</hi> the <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> but the <hi>circumſtances;</hi> not only the <hi>matter</hi> of worſhip,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:97618:61"/>but the <hi>manner:</hi> And though the matter be <hi>good,</hi> if the manner of performance be <hi>naught,</hi> God doth not regard it. You ſee what hee ſaith to the <hi>Jewes, He that ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth, is as he who killed a man, and hee that kils a Lamb, as if he cut off a Dog's head, and he who burneth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, as hee who bleſſeth an Idoll,</hi> Iſa.
<note place="margin">Iſa. 66.3.</note> 66.3. Theſe ſeem ſtrange ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions. What, were not theſe ſuch duties as God commanded? Doth not God <hi>command</hi> ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice? &amp;c. Yes, but becauſe they did them not in that <hi>manner</hi> God commanded, therefore were they abominable to him. If therefore thou gives God the <hi>bulk</hi> of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward performance, without the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of devotion, thou deals by him as <hi>Prometheus</hi> by <hi>Jupiter,</hi> who did eat the fleſh, and preſent him with nothing but bones, covered over with skin; Or, to uſe the Scripture phraſe, <hi>you compaſs God
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:97618:61"/>with a lie,</hi> Hoſ. 11.12.
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 11.12</note> Thou gives him the <hi>ſhell</hi> of outward perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, but not the <hi>kernell</hi> of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward devotion: thou gives him a <hi>body</hi> without a ſoul; And as the <hi>body</hi> without the ſoul is dead and ſtinks, ſo doth that <hi>ſervice</hi> which wants the ſpirit: As God's <hi>will</hi> doth command <hi>ſervice,</hi> ſo our <hi>will</hi> and <hi>affections</hi> muſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form <hi>ſervice.</hi> Though our will muſt be no inſtrument of <hi>deviſing ſervice,</hi> yet it muſt be an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in <hi>performing ſervice.</hi> Though God will not own <hi>will-worſhip</hi> in regard of <hi>preſcription,</hi> yet he will own it in regard of <hi>performance,</hi> and none elſe.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee God commands it, and therefore, &amp;c.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Impü Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt, ſed indè nec mel, nec o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt, &amp;c.</hi> Ambr. <hi>Ser. de coena.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Becauſe otherwiſe wee get no good by this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, no good of Comfort, nor none of Grace. If indeed the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments did <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:97618:62"/>Grace; or if that this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were an Inſtrument for the begetting of Grace in graceleſs hearts, then might you get good, though you came unpreparedly. The word, it is ſet up for that end, to be the inſtrument of regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and therefore, though you come unpreparedly thither, yet you may be wrought upon there.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nemo bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus qui non ex ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo bonus.</hi> Aug.</note> Many that have come to the Word with purpoſe to ſcoff, to taunt, to deride, nay, to inſnare and accuſe, who yet have been wrought on there, and ſent away other men. Were the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſet up for ſuch an end, to beget grace, where there is no grace, then might you get good, though you come unprepared<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and unſanctifiedly thither; but as I have told you, it was never ſet up for ſuch an end: here its true, <hi>habenti dabitur,</hi> to him that hath ſhall be given; he
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:97618:62"/>that hath grace ſhall in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe improve his graces, but he that comes graceleſs hither, goes graceleſs away, nay, worſe then he came, which is the next Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Becauſe otherwiſe we get much hurt.</p>
            <p>The Ordinances are not idle, but operative, they either work for <hi>life,</hi> or they work for <hi>death.</hi> As <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of the Word, it was the ſavour of life and of death; ſo I may ſay of every Ordinance. There is never a time you come to hear the Word, but you are ſet a ſtep neerer heaven or hell: ſo never a time you come to receive the Sacraments, &amp;c. The <hi>fruit</hi> of the tree of Knowledge of good and evill might be <hi>wholſome</hi> in it ſelf: yet <hi>Adam</hi> did <hi>eat</hi> his death, when he taſted of it contrary to God's command. So here the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, though in it ſelf it be
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:97618:63"/>good, yet it becomes the bane and deſtruction of thoſe ſouls, who partake thereof unworthily: As the Ordinances of God are <hi>preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> things when God is ſanctified in them; ſo they are <hi>coſtly</hi> things, when prophan'd. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> knew this full well, and therefore hee prayes, <hi>Now the good Lord pardon all thoſe who come to ſeek the God of their Fathers, though they are not prepared according to the preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sanctuary;</hi> he ſaw the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the unſanctified uſe of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</p>
            <p>To be ſhort, it will bring upon thee, 1. Corporall hurt; you ſee this in the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30. <hi>For this cauſe many are weak and ſickly among you, and many are fallen aſleep.</hi> It was ſome Epidemicall diſeaſe, <hi>flagellum inundans,</hi> ſome over-flowing ſcourge, whereby God ſwept away many, in all the quarters of the Church; and will
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:97618:63"/>you know what was the ground, what was the reaſon of it? The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tels us; that in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, it was for this cauſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the prophanation, or unſanctified uſe of this Ordinance, there was <hi>mors in olla,</hi> death in the cup, they par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taked of the cup of the Lord un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, and drank their own death in it; the cup of life was become a cup of death, the blood of pardon a cup of guilt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Spirituall hurt; though God do not break out in viſible judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon the <hi>carkaſſes</hi> of men as formerly, yet the curſe of God eats ſecretly into the <hi>conſciences</hi> of men. You cauſe God to give you up to blindneſs of minde, hardneſs of heart, and theſe are curſes with a witneſs; the curſe of curſes is a hard heart.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It puts you in danger of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall judgement. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tels you ſo, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 11.29. verſe.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:97618:64"/>
               <hi>He that eats and drinks unworthily, eats &amp; drinks his own damnation: Better,</hi> ſaith
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Melius e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat mola aſinaria collo alliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta mergi in pelagus, quam illo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ de ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu Domini buccellam accipere.</hi> Ambr. <hi>de coena.</hi> Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe, that a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone were tied about thy neck, and thou caſt into the midſt of the ſea; then to take the leaſt bit of bread, or drop of wine from the Miniſter, with an unſanctified heart, and polluted conſcience.</hi> And thus much for the doctrinall part, wee will now come to the application.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. If ſo, that whoever hath to do with an Ordinance muſt ſanctifie God in it; and that there is ſo much required before, ſo much in the time, ſo much afterward; Oh! how few then ſhall we finde, that ſanctifie God in this Ordinance? Some there are, who openly prophane this Ordinance, ſome who ſteal a draught of damnation to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, your cloſe and civill men; this is the difference, where the common prophane man goes to
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:97618:64"/>hell the plain road way, this man ſteals to hell behinde the hedge; And indeed, the beſt of men do not ſanctifie God as they ought in them. Alas, what preparation before wee come upon theſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances? What exciting and ſtirring up of our graces? What exerciſe of grace here? Faith, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance? What thankfulneſs? What obedience afterwards? Where is the fruit of ſo many Sermons, Sacraments; have they not been like rain that falls on the rocks? Are not all theſe like ſo many clouds which paſs over our heads, and leave never a drop of moiſture behinde? Are wee not like <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> lean Kine, never the fatter for all our feeding? Are we not like men ſick of an Atrophy, who, though they feed upon ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo good nouriſhment, yet they grow not thereby? Do wee not ſhame our meat, diſcredit
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:97618:65"/>thoſe heavenly dainties, that we thrive no more by them? Other ages, like <hi>Leah,</hi> were bleer-eyed, but fruitfull: ours like <hi>Rachel,</hi> beautifull, but yet barren: Wee anſwer not God's care and coſt towards us; we profit not; wee grow not; and what's the reaſon? Becauſe we do not ſanctifie God as we ought in theſe Ordinances; therefore are we ſo weak in faith, therefore ſo feeble in grace; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore corruptions ſo ſtrong in us: they who look the Ordinances ſhould be means for the perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their ſanctification, they muſt labour to ſanctifie God in them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. Is it ſo? Then it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooves us to enquire, whether we have ſanctified God in theſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances. Wee have to do with God's Ordinances daily, you ſee God requires, who ever have to do with his Ordinances, ſhould
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:97618:65"/>ſanctifie God in them. Let us then ask the Queſtion of our ſelves: Have I ſanctified God in this Ordinance? I have often come to the Sacrament, but have I ſanctified God in it? Now you might know this by looking over the things: 1. Precedent: 2. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant: 3. Subſequent. But at this time I ſhall follow this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod: Would you know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you have ſanctified God in this Ordinance; ſee then, whether you have obſerved: 1. <hi>God's</hi> order: 2. God's rules: 3. God's ends; and this before your coming. 2. whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you have exerciſed <hi>God's</hi> graces in the time. 3. whether you have returned with God's quickenings, God's inlargements, God's inablements afterward.</p>
            <p n="1">1. See whether you have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved God's order. Now God's order is this, to juſtifie a man, put on him the Wedding Garment;
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:97618:66"/>to ſanctifie a man, to beget him anew before he bring him on this Ordinance. 1. Art thou then juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied? Hath God given thee an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt? Hath he diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered thy ſins to thee? Hath he humbled thy ſoul under the ſenſe and burthen of ſin? Hath hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to thee what footing and ground there is in the Word, for receiving graceleſs perſons to life? Hath he cleared to thee the truth, fulneſs, freeneſs, goodneſs of the promiſe? Hath he brought thy ſoul over to aſſent to the truth, imbrace the goodneſs, reſt upon the firmneſs of it; and to bring all this home to thy own ſoul? Thou art a man who art juſtified, and God calls thee hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to put his Seal to thy Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that thou mayeſt be aſſured for ever, that Chriſt is thine, and thou Chriſts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Art thou a man ſanctified, renewed, regenerated? Hath God
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:97618:66"/>wrought a through, an univerſall, ſpirituall change; I ſay ſpirituall, not a partiall, morall, formall change, but a ſpirituall reall uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall change. That thou haſt a new judgement, new will, new af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; Whereas before there was diſagreement, now there is a bleſſed conformity between God and thee in all things; thou ſeeſt as God ſees, loves as God loves; thou differs as much from thy ſelf, as if another ſoul lived in the ſame body; thou wert once dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, now light in the Lord; once dead, now alive; once blinde, now ſeeſt? Thou art a man whom God calls hither to ſtrengthen and nouriſh his own work in thee. As the maid whom Chriſt raiſed from death, hee ſaid, Give her meat; ſo Chriſt having raiſed thee from the death of ſin to the life of grace, hee calls thee hither, that thou may have meat for the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:97618:67"/>nouriſhment of ſpirituall life in thee; and this is God's order.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You may know whether you have ſanctified God in an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, if you examine, whether you have obſerved God's rules. Now the grand rule is Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which lies in two things:
<list>
                  <item>1. In <hi>Examination.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Excitation</hi> of our graces.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Examination,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Let a man examine himſelf, and ſo let him eat, &amp;c.</hi> which examination is more generall or more ſpeciall.</p>
            <p n="1">1. More generall, of all our ſins; thoſe before, and thoſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our effectuall calling.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of our Graces. 1. What knowledge of God: 2. What faith: 3. what repentance: 4. what love: 5. what hunger &amp; thirſt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is more ſpeciall: 1. how the ſoul hath carried it ſelf under former <hi>Sacraments,</hi> &amp; in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſince the laſt <hi>Sacrament:</hi> what
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:97618:67"/>good it hath gotten; what more ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of faith; what more weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>corruption;</hi> what more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of grace; what more ability to ſerve <hi>God;</hi> and what evil it hath done; all which ſhould be ſet on upon the ſoul, with the many ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations, being ſins againſt vowes, promiſes, againſt cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which doth adde much guilt to ſin, and double the offence. 2. The ſoul is to examine it ſelf, how it ſtands for preſent; what aptneſs, what fitneſs for the duty; what Sacramentall ſorrow; what faith to cloſe w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> God in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent offer, what fitneſs to joyn w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> its fellow-members in holy <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> and love; what hungring and thirſting after <hi>Chriſt</hi> in this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; what ſpirituall appetite; what preſent diſpoſition of ſoul to renew bonds and covenants with God in this Ordinance.</p>
            <p>Of theſe and the like are we to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:97618:68"/>examine our ſelves, that's the firſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is required <hi>Excitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of our graces, that wee ſtir up our faith, our repentance, our hunger and thirſt, &amp;c. 1. Our faith to cloſe with a new offer of Chriſt: 2. Our repentance to mourn afreſh: our hunger and thirſt after Chriſt tendered here. Theſe are God's rules, and if ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, God is ſanctified; and that is the ſecond.</p>
            <p n="3">3. You may know whether you have ſanctified God in this Ordinance, if you examine whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you have obſerved God's ends. Now God's ends are many; <hi>viz.</hi> 1. to glorifie God: 2. to get ſtrength againſt our corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: 3. to get increaſes for our graces. But I ſhall only name one, ſet down by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23. <hi>Do this in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of mee.</hi> Chriſt did a great work for us, and hee is deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:97618:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>it may may not be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; He hath taken care it ſhould be remembred both in heaven and in earth. As he remembers it in heaven, it being a part of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for us there, to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent his blood and ſufferings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God; As under the Law, the Prieſt, when he had offered the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, was to go with the blood before the Altar and Mercy-ſeat, and ſhew it to the Lord: So Chriſt, having offered himſelf a ſacrifice, preſents his blood with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the vail, appearing in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God to intercede for us. And as hee hath taken care to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it in heaven;
<note place="margin">Heb. 9.24.</note> ſo he hath taken care to keep it in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance on earth. And therfore he hath ſet up this <hi>ordinance,</hi> to ſhew forth his death, to put us in mind of his ſufferings: &amp; chargeth us to <hi>do this in remembrance of him.</hi> And when we obſerve this end truly &amp;
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:97618:69"/>rightly as wee ought, then do we ſanctifie God in this Ordinance; I ſay truly and rightly, for every remembrance will not ſerve the turn. 1. It muſt be a cordiall and hearty remembrance; wee muſt remember him with an affected heart; in Religion,
<note n="*" place="margin">Quod cor non facit, noa ſit.</note> what the heart doth not, is not done: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny remember him in a bare hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall way; to recount his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, and yet their heart not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. It is not enough to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member Chriſt in the head, but you muſt remember him in the heart; words of knowledge im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply affection: It muſt be cordiall. 2. It muſt be a gratefull and thankefull remembrance; and there is great cauſe; it is the top-mercy, that which purchaſed all for us; Look on all coming ſwimming in a ſtream of blood; See upon all your mercies ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, The price of blood; and you
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:97618:69"/>will ſee great cauſe to be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. 3. It muſt be a mourning bleeding remembrance: So to look on him pierced, as to be pierced; on him wounded, as to be wounded, &amp;c. And indeed, who can look upon Chriſt in blood; who can behold what he hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, and conceive himſelf to be the actor of all this, and yet the ſharer in all the fruit and benefit; for though we were actors of it, yet hee put us not out of his Will and Teſtament; he did not except againſt us in the parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the fruit of it: who can thus behold him, but muſt weep over Chriſt, as the old Prophet over the other; alas my brother, alas my brother! ſo, alas my CHRIST, alas my CHRIST. 4. It muſt be a crucifying remembrance; ſuch a remembrance of Chriſt cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as crucifies our ſinfull af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, our luſts and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:97618:70"/>as deals by ſin,
<note place="margin">Pro me Dei filius jugulatus, &amp; iterum me peccare dilectat.</note> as ſin hath dealt by Chriſt; kills ſin, as ſin hath killed Chriſt; Oh! ſay, ſhall I give life to that which hath been the death of Chriſt? ſhall I che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh that hath killed Chriſt? ſhall I take pleaſure in that hath been ſo bitter to Chriſt? ſhall I count that light which hath been ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie to him? ſhall I love and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome the knife hath killed my husband? Under the Law, if an <hi>Ox</hi> goared a man, the <hi>Ox</hi> was to die; and ſhall ſin kill Chriſt, and ſhall it not die for it? ſuch a crucifying remembrance it muſt be, as makes us take up weapons againſt ſin; And he that thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members Chriſt, obſerves God's end; and hee who obſerves God's ends, doth ſanctifie God in his Ordinance.</p>
            <p>Well then, would you know whether you have ſanctified God in this Ordinance; ſee if you have
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:97618:70"/>obſerved God's order, God's rules, God's ends, before you come; and ſo much for the firſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Would you know whether you have ſanctified <hi>God</hi> in this <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance,</hi> ſee if you have exerciſed <hi>God's graces</hi> in the time, what thoſe are, and how to be exerciſed, I have ſhewed at large.</p>
            <p n="3">3. See whether you do return home w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> God's quicknings, with God's inlargements, w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> God's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ablements? are you more humble? more ſerviceable? Are you more thankfull? Do you find corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons weakned? your graces ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened? Doth your indeavours afterward anſwer your care and conſcience before? Is your heart ſet further againſt ſin? Are the wayes of God more lovely to you? Are your ſouls knit neerer to God, your ſpirits more infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with love of him? Theſe are plain demonſtrations that you have ſanctified God in this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:97618:71"/>and that God hath ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied it to you. But now on the contrary, let me tell you: 1. If thou haſt broken God's order and method; that thou haſt come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a graceleſs, Chriſtleſs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; the ſoul never yet awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſee ſin, and be humbled for it. Thou knowſt what ſin is in the Catechiſme, but doſt not know what ſin is upon the conſcience; Thou canſt tell mee what faith is in the book, but art not acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the working of it in thy ſoul; and what repentance is, but yet a ſtranger to it; The day is yet to come wherein thou ſet thy ſelf to mourn, and break thy heart for ſin. Where are the chambers? where the cloſets? where the bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides? that can bear witneſs of thy mourning for ſin? And yet doſt thou come? Thou breakſt God's order, and ſo art a prophaner of this holy Table. 2. If thou breakſt God's rules, that thou doſt
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:97618:71"/>not prepare thy ſelf by examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and excitation of thy graces, but ruſheſt into God's preſence, breaks in upon this Ordinance, without any ſutable affections to it, thou art a prophaner of this Ordinance, &amp;c. 3. If thou doſt not obſerve God's ends, but comes hither, as many do: ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to avoid ſcandall, or the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of men; or, for cuſtome, or, for faſhion ſake; becauſe others come, therefore thou wilt not ſtay away; or (which I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expreſs with abhorrencie and deteſtation enough) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou ſhalt ſit at thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's table that day, and go into the fields afterward. Thou art a prophaner of this ordinance; And, Oh! that we had ſome <hi>Tir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhatha</hi> to drive theſe away: Wee read in <hi>Ezra</hi> 2.61, 62. that <hi>Tirſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> would not ſuffer the ſons of <hi>Koſſe</hi> and <hi>Barzilli</hi> to eat of the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:97618:72"/>holy things, becauſe their genea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies were not found regiſtred among them: If thou be not in the book of life, if thy name be not written in the genealogies of the <hi>Saints,</hi> thou art not fit to come.</p>
            <p>In the want of coercive power to fence this Ordinance, give me leave to put a few places to you to conſider: The firſt is in <hi>Titus</hi> 1.15. <hi>To the unclean all is unclean.</hi> the ſecond is in the <hi>Proverbs</hi> 21.27. <hi>The prayers of the wicked are abomination.</hi> The third, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.18. <hi>Hee that regardeth iniquity in his heart, &amp;c.</hi> though hee never come to act it in this life, <hi>God will not regard his prayers:</hi> The fourth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.16. <hi>What haſt thou to do, to take my covenant into thy mouth, and hateſt to be reformed, &amp;c.</hi> And if this will not prevail, reade and tremble, thou prophane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29. <hi>Hee that eateth and drinketh unworthily, &amp;c.</hi> Hee
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:97618:72"/>is made guilty of Chriſt's death, as <hi>Pilate, Herod, Judas,</hi> the <hi>Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> were; Hee eats and drinks damnation to himſelf, and for this cauſe many were ſick, weak and fallen aſleep; And to this adde the example of the unbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den gueſt, who came without a wedding Garment, it fared ill with them that came not, but worſe with him, which tels us, an unſanctified preſence is worſe then a prophane abſence. But yet wilt thou adventure? doſt thou finde any thing in the Sacrament to incourage thee to come? Let us look upon it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſeverall names and noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, under which its preſented.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Its called a Seal, and is the Sacrament any incouragement to thee under this notion; unto whom the Word doth promiſe nothing, the Sacrament ſeals no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; but the Word promiſeth
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:97618:73"/>nothing to unregenerate men. All God's Word is againſt thee, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for thee, and therefore here is but poor incouragement, the ſeal annexed to a Deed, doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it to none, but ſuch to whom the Deed was made: So here, the Sacrament being the ſeal of the Covenant, belongs to none, but thoſe to whom the Covenant is made. Now art thou out of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, one that hath no intereſt in Chriſt? thou haſt nothing here.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Its called a Communion: 1. A Communion of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, one with another: 2. A communion of the members with the head. Now, till thou be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Chriſt, thou haſt nothing here; Chriſt derives influence onely to branches, life onely to his members;
<note n="*" place="margin">Qui vult vivere in capite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet eſſe in corpore. Caput cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris ſui caput, non alieni.</note> hee muſt be in the Son, that hath life from him; he that hath the Son hath life, and he that hath not the Son hath not life.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:97618:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>3. It's called a Supper, the Lord's Supper. Now, is this any incouragement for thee to come, who art a prophane perſon?</p>
            <p>There are three things requiſite in the perſons that goe to a ſupper:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Life.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Appetite.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Apparell.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Life:</hi> Dead men cannot feed; Chriſt never ſpread his table for dead men; if thou be not alive, thou art not called hither to feed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Appetite:</hi> What ſhall they do at a ſupper that have no ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, no appetite? and what do you here, who have no hunger, no thirſting after Chriſt, you that never apprehended what the want of Chriſt, nor never knew the worth of Chriſt?</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Apparell:</hi> No man will go naked to a Feaſt; your apparell here is the Wedding Garment; <hi>Chriſt</hi> for juſtification, <hi>Chriſt</hi> for ſanctification; and he that came
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:97618:74"/>without this, you ſee what became of him; it had been better he had ſtayed away; it fared better with them then with him. An unſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified preſence will be found as bad as a prophane abſence. Thoſe that draw neer to God in an <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> and do not ſanctifie God in it, God will be ſanctified upon them; And that is the third and laſt Doctrine which wee now come unto, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God will be ſanctified upon every one who do not ſanctifie him in his <hi>ordinances.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> In the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of which, wee will ſhew,</p>
            <p n="1">1. What is meant by God's ſanctifying himſelf on men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Why God wil ſanctify him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf on thoſe that do not ſanctifie him in Ordinances, and ſo wee ſhall come to application.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the firſt, What is meant by God's ſanctifying himſelf on a man.</p>
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:97618:74"/>
            <p>For the anſwer of which, I conceive that place w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> I named in the beginning, <hi>Ezek.</hi> c. 28. v. 22. will afford us ſome help; <hi>When I have executed my judgments on her, then will I be ſanctified in her.</hi> Upon which <hi>Jerome,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catio Dei eſt paena pecca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tium.</note> God is ſanctified in the puniſhment of offenders: ſo you ſee it in the <hi>Text,</hi> God's puniſhment of <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> was the occaſion of the word; <hi>I will be ſanctified.</hi>—</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then God doth ſanctifie himſelf on men when hee inflicts corporall puniſhments upon men for prophaning his Ordinance: as you ſee here, and the like, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29. <hi>For this cauſe many are ſick,</hi> — &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God ſanctifies himſelf on men, when hee inflicts ſpirituall puniſhment upon men, &amp;c. <hi>viz.</hi> ſecurity, blindneſs, hardneſs; when men do not walk ſutably to the light of Ordinances, hee takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:97618:75"/>either light or ſight, either ordinances or men's eyes, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they might not ſee, — <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. God doth ſanctifie himſelf on men who prophane his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, when he doth inflict eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall puniſhments upon men; this ſee in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29. <hi>Hee who eateth and drinketh unworthily, eateth and drinketh damnation to himſelf;</hi> that which for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent makes him obnoxious to damnation, and ſhall in the end fix him in flames, lay him in hell, if he do not repent; yea, and the deepeſt cellars in hell, are for them who have lived in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation of Ordinances. And this in brief ſhall ſuffice to tell you what is meant by God's ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying himſelf upon men.</p>
            <p>We come to the ſecond thing propounded, what are the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons God doth ſanctifie himſelf on thoſe that do not ſanctifie him in Ordinances.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:97618:75"/>1. <hi>In terrorem,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> for the terror and dread of all prophane perſons, that when you hear how God hath puniſhed others, who have prophaned the Ordinances of God, you might tremble, and not dare to prophane them. If God ſhould only threaten, and ſhould not ſometime execute his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure upon ſuch as were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaners of his Ordinances, men would not fear to prophane them. They would but make chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren-play of all the threatnings of God, as they did in 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 3.3. <hi>There ſhall come in the laſt day,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſcoffers,</hi> ſuch as ſhall make children-play of all the threats of God, and look upon them but as harmleſs Bug-beares, to keep them in awe only. But when God doth back a threatning with a puniſhment, as you ſee hee did here in the Text, and on the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> this ſtrikes dread into
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:97618:76"/>the hearts of prophane perſons.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> God doth it in <hi>cautionem,</hi> for warning, That others <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, might be our <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, others woes might be our warnings; others ſufferings might be ſtanding Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to us, preaching this leſſon, to beware of the like ſin, leſt you ſhare in the ſame puniſhment; therefore God puniſhes ſinne in ſome,
<note n="*" place="margin">Ne in ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os graſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> that others might beware; <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.20. <hi>And thoſe which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſhall hear and fear, and do no more wickedly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vt te con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diret.</note> &amp;c. <hi>Lot's</hi> wife was turned into a pillar of ſalt, to ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thee, ſaith the Father: Beware of back-ſliding. <hi>Moſes</hi> was denied entrance into the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> for his murmuring and unbelief, that thou might beware: <hi>David</hi> was puniſhed for his uncleanneſs, that thou might take heed: The man was ſtoned for gathering of a few ſticks on the <hi>Sabbath day,</hi> to teach us to beware of prophaning
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:97618:76"/>the Sabbath. <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed for her Idolatry, <hi>Babylon</hi> for her pride, <hi>Sodome</hi> for unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the old world for drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that theſe might ſtand up as warnings to us. As the Apoſtle ſhewes at large, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5. to the 12. <hi>Let us not be Idolaters, as ſome of them were,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>All theſe things hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened them, for enſamples and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition to us.</hi> We may well ſay of all, <hi>Lege exemplum, ne exemplum fias,</hi> Read the example leſt thou be made an example. Reade the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> deſtroyed for his oppreſſion, contempt of God, and hardneſs of heart; and beware thou of the ſame ſins, leſt God make thee an example, &amp;c. Reade the example of <hi>Herod</hi> deſtroyed for <hi>his</hi> pride, <hi>Jezabel</hi> for <hi>her</hi> paint, <hi>Saul</hi> for <hi>his</hi> diſobedience; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware thou of the like ſin, leſt God deſtroy thee. And as in all others, ſo in this ſin of prophanation of
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:97618:77"/>this <hi>ordinance,</hi> God doth thus pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the prophaners of it, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers might beware of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation; therfore did he puniſh the <hi>Corinthians</hi> with ſickneſs, with death, weakneſs, for the unworthy partaking of this Ordinance; that ſo they that remained alive, and wee that follow them, might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of the like ſin, leſt wee par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the like, or a worſe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for uſually, God's ſecond blowes are more heavie then the firſt: they were the firſt ſufferers for this ſin; and if they were ſo heavily puniſhed, what may wee then expect, if wee do prophane this Ordinance?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 3.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>In manifeſtationem ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiae,</hi> to declare his juſtice againſt ſin. God, hee made a threatning againſt this; and if God ſhould not ſometimes puniſh offenders, either men would think they did not offend; or if they did, that
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:97618:77"/>God was not juſt, becauſe he did not puniſh. Therefore God to cleare his juſtice, and convince men of ſin, doth often ſanctifie himſelf on ſuch as prophane, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Ad removendum ſcandala;</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> to take away ſcandals: as you ſee he doth ſometime puniſh his own people, becauſe their ſins occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſcandall. God was more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured by the uncleanneſs of <hi>David,</hi> then by all the filth of <hi>Sodome;</hi> and therefore, becauſe hee had cauſed the name of God to be blaſphemed, God puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth him, though hee pardoned him; and as hee doth puniſh his own people, if they ſin, becauſe they have given occaſion to the wicked within the Church to blaſpheme: ſo hee puniſhes the wicked, becauſe they give occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to them, who are without the Church to blaſpheme; What will <hi>Heathens, Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans</hi> ſay?
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:97618:78"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ecce qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſunt qui Chriſtum colunt! aut hoc non eſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelium, aut vos non eſtis E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelici.</note> Behold what manner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons they are, who worſhip this <hi>Chriſt!</hi> This is either no Goſpel, or you are no <hi>Goſpellers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 5. Why <hi>God</hi> doth ſanctify himſelf on ſuch as do not ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him in an <hi>Ordinance,</hi> is <hi>to hold up his great Name, and the purity of his Ordinances.</hi> God could no way hold up his dread, his fear, his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, his glory, his purity &amp; truth of his Word, if God ſhould not puniſh ſuch as prophane his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances. You ſee what a conceit thoſe had of God in <hi>Pſalme</hi> 50. <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. becauſe God did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to puniſh offenders: <hi>When thou ſaweſt a thief, thou conſentedſt with him, &amp;c. Theſe things haſt thou done, and I kept ſilent;</hi> I did not preſently come forth to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh thee, to execute my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on thee. And what was the fruit of it? What conceit did this forbearance of God work in
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:97618:78"/>thoſe that were guilty.
<note place="margin">Scelerum paetronum.</note> 
               <hi>Thou thought I was altogether ſuch a one as thy ſelf;</hi> that is, that I was one who liked and approved of thy doings; thou thought thou didſt not amiſs, becauſe I did not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh. Here you ſee God was wronged by forbearing, and not executing judgement upon offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: And there was no way for God to cleare himſelf, to hold up his great name, but this way, to make them know what they had done, and therefore it followes: <hi>I will ſet thy ſins in order before thine eyes. Oh! conſider this, yee that forget God, leſt, &amp;c.</hi> So you ſee God doth puniſh offenders to hold up his great name; and there is no other way to hold up the name of God, the purity and holineſs of God, but by puniſhment of offenders: You come to the Sacrament, and you prophane this Ordinance, God hath threatened death and
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:97618:79"/>damnation to every unworthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver. Why, but you know God doth not execute ſentence ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily on you, and therefore you think you do not offend; ſure <hi>God</hi> is pleaſed with it. And therefore <hi>God</hi> to uphold his Name, the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his <hi>Ordinance,</hi> and make you know what you have done, doth ſanctifie himſelf upon thoſe who do not ſanctifie him in this <hi>Ordinance;</hi> ſometimes in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting viſible &amp; corporall judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on offenders, as you ſee in the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> alwayes inviſible and ſpirituall judgements for the preſent, and eternall judgement if you do not repent. And this you ſee <hi>God</hi> doth to hold up his name, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> otherwiſe would be polluted by men. As in nature for preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole, particulars pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: Its better one periſh then unity it ſelf: So here, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the glory of <hi>God,</hi>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:97618:79"/>(which is worth ten thouſand of our lives and ſouls, as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſaid to <hi>David) God</hi> doth inflict puniſhments upon offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. And there is no other way to preſerve or make whole, and repair the honour, glory of God, &amp;c. Men that will not learn by the Word, muſt be taught by works; if the Word will not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with you, to forbear the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation of his <hi>Ordinances,</hi> then his works come in. If you will be ſo ſenſuall and brutiſh, that you will ſee nothing to be ſin, but what you feel to be ſin in <hi>God's</hi> hand upon you, you ſhall feel blows enough; <hi>A rod is for the back of a fool.</hi> Take this with you, What ever you will not learn by faith, you ſhall be taught by ſenſe. <hi>God</hi> makes men feel thoſe things to be evill by ſenſe, which by faith they would not believe to be evil. When the word will not prevail
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:97618:80"/>with men to forbear prophanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any ordinance, or any ſin, then from <hi>word</hi> he goes to works; lays afflictions, judgements, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts on men. And happy tis if the works bring men again to the word, when <hi>Schola crucis</hi> is <hi>Schola lucis,</hi> when <hi>God's</hi> houſe of correction is a ſchool of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: So ſaith <hi>David, Bleſſed is the man whom thou chaſtiſeſt and teacheſt in thy law.</hi> It was ſo you ſee with the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> the word did not prevail; <hi>God</hi> goes to his works, inflicts puniſhments on them, ſickneſs, weakneſs, death; and then hee comes to the word again: <hi>For this cauſe many are ſick.</hi> And no doubt, but word upon works, was more prevalent with them, then when it went alone.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>6</label> 6. To declare his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred againſt ſin: <hi>God</hi> hates all ſin; and the neerer a ſin comes to <hi>God,</hi> the more he hates it. Now this
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:97618:80"/>is neer him, you diſhonour his Name; his Ordinances are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, they are his name; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>God</hi> will not hold ſuch guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, &amp;c. Thus you ſee I have ſhewed you, that <hi>God</hi> will ſanctifie himſelf upon al thoſe who do not ſanctifie him in an <hi>ordinance:</hi> And I have ſhewed you the grounds &amp; reaſons of it; now to application.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. Oh! then take heed thou who art a prophane perſon, a ſwearer, a drunkard, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, leſt <hi>God</hi> make this true of thee this day, and raiſe his glory out of thy ruines. Thou wilt not be warned by the word, look for works; thou whom the examples of others will not make to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, take heed, leſt <hi>God</hi> do here make thee an example. It was the third Captain's wiſdome in the 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.13, 14. who, when he ſaw <hi>God's</hi> viſible judgements upon the two former Captains, hee
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:97618:81"/>takes warning thereby, and avoids their ſins; ſo you that are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, when you ſee and heare what <hi>God</hi> hath threatned againſt prophaners of this Ordinance; and what fearfull judgements <hi>God</hi> hath executed upon all unworthy receivers, which are all Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, all graceleſs perſons; Oh! beware of coming hither in thy ſins. God's Word is true; As what hee promiſeth is ſure to come to paſs; ſo what ever hee threatens. And though hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long and defer the time of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, yet your damnation ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7, 8, 9. verſes. <hi>It ſhall ſurely come.</hi> If God ſhould threaten to ſtrike dead every unworthy receiver, you would be afraid to come, and how would it make the beſt of us to look about us, whether we are worthy receivers or not? But alas, what is this threatning
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:97618:81"/>in compariſon of the other, you eat and drink damnation to your ſelves? This is as far above the other, as a temporall is below an eternall; A puniſhment upon the body below the everlaſting wrath of God, and puniſhment of your ſouls. Better you were ſtrucke dead here, then reſerved for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting death hereafter. Thy body eſcapes here (and yet I cannot aſſure thee of that; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who were God's own peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, were ſtruck with death and ſickneſs; and I cannot aſſure thee that God will not deſtroy thee with the bread in thy mouth, as hee did the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> with the <hi>Quails</hi> in theirs. God hath threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened, and we know not whether he will execute, yea, or no: God ſaid, <hi>I will not hold him guiltleſs that takes my Name in vain.</hi> Examples we have; but other examples are worn out; who knowes whether
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:97618:82"/>he will not give freſh examples, and deal by thee as he did by <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dab,</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> in the Text, even in the face of the whole congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, deſtroy thee with fire from heaven; that all may feare, thou went with them, but from fire to fire, from a <hi>deſtruction</hi> by fire, to <hi>preſervation</hi> in fire, from tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to eternall burnings. But ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that God ſhould forbear his ſtroke now, yet it is certain to come.
<note place="margin">Quorum ultio repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitur in futurum.</note> And wo be to them, whoſe vengeance is reſerved for another day. Ah, it will come then with a witneſs, then with load enough, when the guilt of al thy prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this glorious <hi>ordinance;</hi> come together; and therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, beware as thou loves thy <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy;</hi> nay, thy <hi>ſoul,</hi> &amp; that for ever, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of unworthy partaking, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. If ſo, Oh! then look to it, you who go on in a way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation of Gods Ordinances.
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:97618:82"/>God hath ſaid, hee will be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of them who draw neer to him. And doſt thou believe this? Is it true, or is it falſe? I know thou dare not but ſay this is truth, God himſelf ſpeaks it. Well then, this being a truth what may thou <hi>expect</hi> who art a <hi>prophaner</hi> of his Ordinances? And to all thy prophanations, as it was ſaid of <hi>Herod,</hi> he added this, that he caſt <hi>John</hi> in priſon; ſo you adde this to all the reſt, the prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Ordinance of the Lords Supper. Oh! this is a ſin, for which God will not bear with thee. If God would not bear with his <hi>own people,</hi> the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> who yet had grace, were <hi>habitually</hi> diſpoſed, were ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, ſanctified, and wanted only <hi>actuall</hi> preparation and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, in the Ordinance, how ſhall he <hi>bear</hi> with thee thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſon, graceleſs perſon?
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:97618:83"/>If God deal thus with the <hi>green</hi> tree, what ſhall become of the <hi>dry</hi> tree? If God deal thus with his own, what ſhall become of thee? If thus with the <hi>bearing,</hi> what ſhall become of the <hi>barren</hi> tree? If judgement begin at the houſe of God, where ſhall the wicked and ſinners appear? Anſwer me that if thou canſt. If God will be <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified</hi> upon his <hi>ſanctified</hi> ones, what of thee? If God doth puniſh the want of <hi>circumſtances,</hi> what wil he do to thee, who wants the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> the main requiſite? But it may be thou thinks there is no ſuch matter, theſe are but Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bears, &amp;c. for thy part, thou haſt come hither, and gone home, and found no hurt. And haſt thou ſo? Bleſs not thy ſelf in that, there is the more behind. A black and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall <hi>ſhowre</hi> of <hi>wrath</hi> is ſure to fall upon thee one day. This is <hi>true,</hi> God will be ſanctified of them
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:97618:83"/>that come nigh him. And this is true alſo, Hee who eats and drinks unworthily is made guilty of the body and blood of Chriſt; nay, he eats &amp; drinks damnation to himſelf. And this is as true, he who eats and drinks in a Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs condition, eats and drinks un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily. And what doſt thou think will be the <hi>conſequents</hi> of ſuch a ſin? In ſtead of a <hi>drinker</hi> thou becomes a <hi>ſhedder</hi> of the blood of Chriſt, as <hi>Judas,</hi> as <hi>Pilate,</hi> as <hi>Herod.</hi> Look upon the <hi>Jews,</hi> and ſee what it is to be <hi>guilty</hi> of the body and blood of Chriſt. It is the heavieſt curſe in the world, to be guilty of that blood which ſhould ſave you, pardon you: ſhall that which ſhould be a blood of pardon, become a blood of guilt? Oh! what is it to be <hi>guilty</hi> of that blood, ſhould take away guilt? If thou wert <hi>guilty</hi> of all the ſins of men on earth, and damn'd in hell,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:97618:84"/>the <hi>blood</hi> of Chriſt could pardon thee, and take off that <hi>guilt.</hi> But what ſhal take off the <hi>guilt</hi> of that that ſhould take off <hi>guilt?</hi> Oh! ſee what a ſin it is; and in the fear of God, adde not this to all your ſin, to all your ſwearings, your prophanations, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, adde not this to all, to be guilty of the body and blood of Chriſt; aſſure your ſelves, God will not <hi>care</hi> for your bodies, who have no <hi>regard</hi> to the body of his Son; ſhall your <hi>blood</hi> be eſteemed when the <hi>blood</hi> of Chriſt is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned? ſhall your <hi>lives</hi> be priz'd when the <hi>death</hi> of his <hi>Son</hi> is ſleigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? nay, when you by this ſin ſhal crucifie Chriſt again? judge that.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 3. Well then, if the ſin be ſo great, and the puniſhment w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> God hath threatned be ſo terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, what care ought wee to have, wee do not prophane this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance? and what care to <hi>look back</hi>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:97618:84"/>into our lives, and ſee whether we have not prophaned this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. The one, to <hi>prevent ſin</hi> not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, and ſo to <hi>prevent wrath;</hi> the other to <hi>repent</hi> of ſin commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſo to <hi>turn</hi> away wrath. But you will ſay, how ſhal I know whether I have prophaned this Ordinance? For the anſwer of which, I refer yon to what I have ſaid in the ſecond <hi>Doctrine</hi> (where I put the triall upon theſe three Generals: 1. the obſerving Gods order: 2. Gods rules: 3. Gods ends.) I ſhall now adde three more to help to diſcover whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you have been prophaners of this Ordinance yea or no.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When the <hi>Sacraments</hi> work no further good upon thee, thou haſt prophaned this Ordinance. I have told you, the <hi>Sacraments</hi> are not idle, empty things, but <hi>opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> and efficacious toward them who are worthy receivers. Chriſt
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:97618:85"/>cannot be <hi>fed</hi> on, but he muſt <hi>nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi> the ſoul. A man may <hi>feed</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on other <hi>meats</hi> and get no nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, but he who <hi>feeds</hi> on this, he finds <hi>ſpirituall ſtrength</hi> and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment. Now then, when men come hither, and <hi>return</hi> as <hi>empty</hi> as they came, as vile as before, there is no fruit can be ſeen in their <hi>lives</hi> and converſations; here a man may ſuſpect the Ordinance is prophaned. When men were fil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy, and are filthy ſtill, ſwearers, and are ſo ſtill, drunkards, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſo ſtill; this is an evident de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration thou haſt been a prophaner of this Ordinance: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Gods people do not <hi>ever</hi> get the good they expect, <hi>never</hi> get the good they <hi>deſire.</hi> But yet ſome good is gotten, ſome more ſtrength of Grace, ſome more working out of luſt, although for the preſent they cannot appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it. But the other now, they get none, they come graceleſs hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:97618:85"/>and go graceleſs away: and it muſt needs be ſo, this is no Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance for the working of grace in graceleſs perſons, but for the nouriſhing of grace in thoſe whom God hath wrought grace in, as I have ſhewed at large.</p>
            <p>So that is the firſt, when wee get no good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When a man is <hi>worſe</hi> after then before, this is an evident ſign hee hath prophaned this Ordinance. When a man is <hi>ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened</hi> in a <hi>ſtate</hi> of ſin returns with more <hi>violence</hi> to any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſin; as you ſee <hi>Judas,</hi> the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil entred into him, he took fuller and ſtronger poſſeſſion of him; and you ſhall ſee this the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fruit of <hi>prophanation</hi> of this <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance,</hi> men wax worſe &amp; worſe, proceeding from evill to evill. It may be, when firſt they came to receive, they were fearfull; for there is ſome naturall tenderneſs
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:97618:86"/>of conſcience in men, and they are afraid to come to ſo great an Ordinance, without ſome kind of preparation, and therefore it may be they did catch up a book the day before, and ſay a <hi>Prayer</hi> more, carry themſelves demurely. But afterwards, when men are <hi>grown up</hi> in the prophanation of this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, they can look upon all the <hi>threats,</hi> upon all the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments denounced againſt them in this Ordinance, and never ſtart at them, never tremble. And what is the Reaſon they <hi>trembled before,</hi> and do not now, their condition is never the better, it may be farre worſe. Why, here is the reaſon, the <hi>cuſtome</hi> of prophanation of this Ordinance, hath <hi>hardened</hi> them in their way, they now fear nothing, their heart is fortified. They have <hi>ſinned</hi> away thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon principles, that <hi>naturall ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs,</hi> that was once in them;
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:97618:86"/>Sin is an eating thing, it eats out the very heart of every thing w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is good in men. A man may not only ſin away his morall princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, but he may ſin away the very principles of nature. Sin will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver leave till it hath made all as vile as it ſelf, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.26, 27. When men live in the prophanation of this Ordinance, they wax worſe and worſe. That man <hi>runs</hi> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently on in ſin, who <hi>ſets out</hi> from the prophanation of Gods Ordinances, becauſe he <hi>runs</hi> with the <hi>Devils ſtrength,</hi> Satan hath fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his heart with more miſchief. As the <hi>Saints</hi> do run more <hi>active<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> in the wayes of God after, ſo the wicked more <hi>violently</hi> in a way of ſin. The prophanation of this Ordinance doth ſtrengthen men to further ſinne; either as, 1. One ſin doth diſpoſe a man to another, helps the birth of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:97618:87"/>2. Nay, and one ſin doth ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then a man to the commiſſion of another. As one duty of <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi> doth <hi>diſpoſe</hi> and inable to the performance of another: So one ſin doth <hi>diſpoſe</hi> and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion of another. The ſin of unworthy eating doth ſtrengthen to more ſin; Such a man, he gets more heart to ſin: he that dares break through threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings here to ſin, will not ſtick to do it in other caſes. It cauſes God to give us up to blindneſs of minde, hardneſs of heart, &amp;c. which gives Satan further foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in mens hearts, to egge them on to all munner of wickedneſs. You ſee it in <hi>Judas;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if thou finde thy ſelf worſe in life and converſation, there's a manifeſt ſign thou haſt propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this Ordinance.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Sign of propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> When a man feeds upon nothing but the <hi>outward element,</hi>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:97618:87"/>the Bread and Wine, and not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſt in the promiſe, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes this Ordinance. If thou feedſt not upon <hi>panem Chriſtum,</hi> as well as <hi>panem Chriſti,</hi> the <hi>Bread</hi> which is the Lord, as well as the <hi>Bread</hi> of the Lord, thou propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt this Ordinance. A man may eat Bread, and drink Wine in an <hi>ordinary</hi> way, and not ſin; but hee who eats Bread, and drinks Wine in the way of an <hi>Ordinance,</hi> and doth not feed upon Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, hee is a prophaner of this <hi>Ordinance.</hi> Now thou canſt not feed upon Chriſt in a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> till thou have fed on Chriſt in a <hi>promiſe.</hi> Thou canſt not feed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſt <hi>ſacramentally,</hi> till thou firſt feed upon Chriſt <hi>ſpiritually.</hi> And haſt thou ever fed upon Chriſt in the <hi>promiſe?</hi> Did ever God <hi>diſcover</hi> ſin to thee, and humble thy ſoul for it? Did ever God <hi>reveal</hi> Chriſt to thee, and
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:97618:88"/>bring thy heart to cloſe with him? then thou haſt fed on Chriſt, and mayſt come. But hee who never fed on Chriſt ſpiritually, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver taſt him ſacramentally. Thou haſt no organ, no <hi>eye</hi> of faith to ſee Chriſt here, nor no <hi>mouth</hi> of faith to taſt him here, no <hi>liſe</hi> to deſire him, and therefore cannot feed on him. And hee who doth not feed upon Chriſt here, is a prophaner of this Ordinance. A man may feed upon Chriſt, and never taſt of the Bread and Wine, and yet have the ſame benefits, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.53. a place which is ſpoken of the ſpirituall feeding on <hi>Chriſt</hi> out of the uſe of the Sacrament. But a man cannot <hi>feed</hi> upon the the Bread and Wine, and not <hi>feed</hi> upon Chriſt, but hee prophanes this Ordinance; Chriſt <hi>without theſe</hi> may be fed upon, but not <hi>theſe without</hi> Chriſt. If thy <hi>body</hi> feed on theſe, and thy <hi>ſoul</hi> doth
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:97618:88"/>not feed on Chriſt, thou art a prophaner of this Ordinance. Well then, to ſum up all in this, Would you know whether you have prophaned this Ordinance?
<note place="margin">Recapitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. See if you have obſerved Gods order, &amp;c. If thou haſt not obſerved Gods order, that thou comes hither in a Chriſtleſs, graceleſs condition, unjuſtified, unſanctified; wants thou faith; wants thou repentance; wants thou hunger and thirſt; wants thou knowledge? thou art a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaner of it. And alas, of that little triall I have had in this laſt <hi>matter,</hi> viz. <hi>knowledge,</hi> I have found great want. You would admire if I ſhould tell you the ſenſleſs anſwers I have had; I ſpeak not of all, there are ſome who are but green in yeers, yet are ripe in knowledge; but yet many who are grave in yeers extreme ignorant: Ask them what a Sacrament is,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:97618:89"/>they cannot tell; ask them for what end they come to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they tel me to nouriſh their bodies; what God requires, they know not: and ſuch anſwers, that a man might have as much <hi>comfort</hi> to give the Sacrament of the Lords Supper to a child, as to ſuch ignorant creatures. I am ſure there is leſs ſin in one then the other, and there is not much more knowledge. It is true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if a man had never ſo much <hi>knowledge,</hi> if he could tell mee as much as any in the world, of the nature of God, of Chriſt, of the Sacraments, &amp;c. yet without <hi>Grace,</hi> this would not make him a worthy Receiver. The Devill knowes more then moſt men, for the ſpeculative part; yet what is he the better for that? But yet if a man be ignorant, hee muſt needs be a prophaner of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. A man may have know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and yet not have Grace, but
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:97618:89"/>if he have no knowledge, he is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly graceleſs. So the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſaith, <hi>Without knowledge the minde is not good.</hi> We have a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Proverb, <hi>Hee that made us ſave us.</hi> But God anſwers that, in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.11.
<note place="margin">Iſa. 27.11.</note> 
               <hi>Yee are a people of no underſtanding, therefore hee that made you will not ſave you, and hee that formed you will ſhew no mercy on you.</hi> And he threatens, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.8.
<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>To come in flaming fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not the Goſpel of Chriſt;</hi> And therefore beware you who are ignorant perſons, of coming, you will prophane this <hi>ordinance:</hi> and you who are grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs perſons, though you ſhould know as much as all the men in the world, come not here, if thou do, thou breaks Gods order, and ſo prophaneſt this Ordinance. 2. If you have not obſerved Gods rules, examined your ſelf, and
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:97618:90"/>excited and ſtirred up your Graces.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If you have not obſerved Gods ends, &amp;c. you will be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaners of this ordinance of <hi>God.</hi> And me thinks this ſhould terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie you, who are prophane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; ſure thou haſt <hi>reaſon</hi> in thee though thou want <hi>grace:</hi> Doſt thou hear what God ſaith, <hi>Hee will be ſanctified of them that come nigh him?</hi> Haſt thou not heard, hee that eats and drinks unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, is made guilty of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and blood of Chriſt? Doth not God ſay, <hi>Who ever eats and drinks unworthily, eats and drinks damnation to himſelf?</hi> And have not I cleared to thee, all Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, graceleſs perſons are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Receivers? And yet wilt thou come? Beware, leſt God ſhew ſome viſible judgement on thee; Beware, leſt God teach thee by workes, who wilt not
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:97618:90"/>learn by word: See what befell <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> here, becauſe they did not ſanctifie God: Reade what befell the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> read what befell the man in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> who came without his wedding garment: <hi>Take him hence, and caſt him into utter darkneſs,</hi> &amp;c. Let former <hi>examples</hi> move thee,
<note place="margin">Lege ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum, ne exemplum fias.</note> leſt God make thee an example. Think, God is the ſame God ſtill, his Glory as dear to him, his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances as precious: As he is the ſame towards the Saints in the wayes of mercy, ſo thou may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect him the ſame to thee in the the wayes of judgement; And if this move thee not, if this will not perſwade with thee to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, I waſh my hands of the guilt of the blood of thy ſoul, I have given thee warning, and thy blood is upon thine own head; And I wiſh the guilt of the blood of Chriſt be not upon thee too.
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:97618:91"/>Let mee then beſeech you, in the bowels of love and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as you love your ſouls, as you love your bodies, as you would not be guilty of your own blood; Nay, as you would not be guilty of the blood of Chriſt; as you would not eat and drink damnation to your ſelves; as you would not provoke God to break in upon you, and inflict his ſevere judgements on you, come not here: Come not here, thou ignorant perſon, thou graceleſs, thou Chriſtleſs perſon, thou ſwearer, thou drunkard, thou co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous perſon; Nay, come not here, who ever you are, who are ſervants to any luſt, who live in any known ſin, leſt God make this good upon thee, which I have preached to thee. That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou doſt not ſanctifie God in this Ordinance, he will ſanctifie himſelf on thee; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:97618:91"/>thou doſt not glorifie him, hee will raiſe his glory out of thy ruines. But whileſt I ſpeak thus ſadly to the bad, let mee not be a terrour to the good. I would not break the bruiſed Reed, nor quench the ſmoaking Flax: As I would not give incouragement to graceleſs perſons, ſo I would not diſcourage the leaſt worke of grace in any: As I would not cheriſh any falſe fire, unſound work; ſo I would not quench any ſpark of God's kindling; haſt thou ſome work of God upon thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit? hath God diſcovered to thee ſin and miſery? hath he humbled thee for it? hath God revealed Chriſt to thee, ſtirred thy heart with deſires, after him; that riches without Chriſt, relations, comforts, the world without Chriſt will not ſatisfie thee? all theſe are like a Feaſt without an appetite, a Paradiſe without a
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:97618:92"/>tree of Life, too low either for thee to feed upon, or to finde comfort &amp; ſatisfaction in them; doſt thou ſeek after Chriſt, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue Chriſt; doſt thou caſt thy ſelf in his arms to ſave, at his feet to ſerve? why, ſuch I would invite;
<note place="margin">Iſa. 55.1.</note> 
               <hi>Ho, every one that thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth, come to the waters;</hi> here cloſe with Chriſt, feed on Chriſt; and to ſuch I would ſay, Chriſt is properly and truly food for your ſouls; and feeding on him your ſouls ſhall live, in grace here, in glory hereafter.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97618:92"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
